<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The memorial of the just shall not rot, or, A collection of some of the letters of that faithful servant of the Lord, William Wilson who departed this life the tenth day of the fifth month 1682 ... together with several testimonies concerning his faithfulness in his day : unto which is added a brief accompt of some of the buffetings, imprisonments, and spoiling of goods he patiently suffered for his testimonies sake.</title>
            <author>Wilson, William, d. 1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11259588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11259588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47206</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47206)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1452:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The memorial of the just shall not rot, or, A collection of some of the letters of that faithful servant of the Lord, William Wilson who departed this life the tenth day of the fifth month 1682 ... together with several testimonies concerning his faithfulness in his day : unto which is added a brief accompt of some of the buffetings, imprisonments, and spoiling of goods he patiently suffered for his testimonies sake.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, William, d. 1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56, [i.e. 58] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and faded, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Contains Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wilson, William, d. 1682.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47206:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47206:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The memorial of the just shall not rot of the Juſt ſhall not Rot.</hi> Or a Short COLLECTION OF Some of the letters of that faithful Servant of the Lord William Wilſon, VVHO Departed this life the tenth day of the fifth Month 1682 at his own Houſe at <hi>Longdale-Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelſteel</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmoreland.</hi> TOGETHER VVith ſeveral Teſtimonies Concerning his faithfulnes in his day. UNTO VVhich is added a brief accompt of ſome of the buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Impriſonments, and ſpoiling of goods he patiently ſuffered for his Teſtimonies ſake.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, he ſhall be as Mount</hi> Sion: <hi>that cannot be moved.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:47206:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. l. 1. for <hi>lay</hi> r. <hi>laid,</hi> l. 26. f. <hi>into</hi> r. <hi>to,</hi> f. <hi>men</hi> r. <hi>me,</hi> p. 7. l. 1. <hi>after</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> l. 5. f.; r. <hi>had,</hi> p. 12. l. 15. f. <hi>with</hi> r. <hi>in the,</hi> p. 13. l. 12. <hi>after that</hi> r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> f. <hi>direct</hi> r. <hi>directs,</hi> l. 32. <hi>after that</hi> r. <hi>it,</hi> p. 14. l. 9. f. <hi>ſin</hi> r. <hi>ſeen,</hi> l, 18. f. <hi>they</hi> r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> l. <hi>laſt</hi> f. <hi>all</hi> r. <hi>his,</hi> p. 22. l. 2. <hi>blot out</hi> W. W. p. 24. l. 12. f. <hi>the from</hi> r. <hi>thee from,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 38 dele <hi>as,</hi> p. 38. l. 1. f. <hi>though</hi> r. <hi>through,</hi> p. 34. l. 30. f. <hi>his</hi> r. <hi>is,</hi> p. 34. l. 17. r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>their,</hi> l. 25. f. <hi>your</hi> r. <hi>you,</hi> p. 37. l. 17. f. <hi>conetenous</hi> r. <hi>covetous,</hi> p. 38. dele <hi>the</hi> 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 40. l. 24. <hi>after not put at,</hi> p. 42. l. 20. f. <hi>Prioners</hi> r. <hi>Priſoner,</hi> p. 43. l. 17. r. <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> p. 53. l. 15. f. <hi>mortal</hi> r. <hi>immortal,</hi> l. 21. f. <hi>have</hi> r. <hi>hear,</hi> l. 26. f. <hi>meſſuge</hi> r. <hi>meſſage,</hi> l. 34. f. <hi>of</hi> r. <hi>for,</hi> p. 56. l. 3. dele out, p. 56 l 3 f <hi>hoeſt</hi> r <hi>honeſt</hi> l. 12. dele <hi>believers,</hi> l. 16. f. <hi>caſting</hi> r. <hi>cauſing.</hi> There are ſeveral other miſtakes which the Reader is deſired to correct.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:47206:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>FRiend whoever thou art that reads the enſuing Treatiſe, may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there are only a few of the Letters and Epiſtles, which have ſince his deceaſe been found in looſe papers; and that many Heavenly Exhortations to friends, which he wrote in his day, are loſt; and but only as it were a few of many here inſerted, for although he was born and educated very meanly in this dark corner of the Earth, and had very little Humane Learning, only he could Read Engliſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> little, yet but ſlowly; and was by his Trade and occupation a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lord was pleaſed to call him (as he did Fiſher-men and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of old) into his Heavenly work and Miniſtery, to bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to his Name in many parts of this Nation, and alſo <hi>Scotland</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> places; and he was a faithful man, and was given up to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> work, and always had a word of Exhortation to the People that he met with, or had to do withal: ſo what thou here ſinds preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thy view, did not proceed from any Humane Education or wiſdom of Man, but only what the Lord was pleaſed to reveal in him by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo is not worded with high Scholaſtick words, but even homely words and plain Countrey ſpeech, being always a man of a very lowly meek Spirit, and eaſie to be intreated; and being he had little Humane Learning is the reaſon why both time and place of ſome of his Writings is not taken notice of: And this I have to ſay concerning him (being one who hath ſeveral times joyned with him as in Arbitration, to end differences between man and man) that he was a very upright honeſt man, and I never found him any way byaſſed by any for whom be was concerned, but always was at work to ſeek out the truth and ground of every thing in difference, and would never countenance deceit, or ſuch as had a mind to wrangle, but did always reprove and diſcountenance ſuch as he found had a mind of Suits and Controverſies; and commonly when he was appointed in ſuch matters he had good ſucceſs, and ſeldom miſſed of his deſired end, for he was a lover of Peace, and ſought it often with all his might, and was alſo an encourager of thoſe that ſought peace, and loved to love in quiet, though he would not have bowed a
<pb facs="tcp:47206:3"/>finger of his hand to ſatisfy the will of man, contrary to what was manifeſted in him, either in payment of Tythes or Prieſt Salaried or when he was brought before Magiſtrates and Rulers for the Exerciſe of his Conſcience to wards God, and for the bleſſed Truths ſake which he profeſſed, and alſo was and now is a true Pofeſſor of, and hath received a Crown of Glory with the God of Truth, whoſe faithful ſervant and true warri ur he was, and his Bow always abode in its perfect ſtrength, to ſhoot an Arrow at all manner of deceipt and hypocriſie, though to the hazzard of his outward man, by the violent hands of wicked and unreaſonable men, yet the Lord was always his deliverer, who now hath taken him to his Eternal reſt, and removed all weights and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens from his ſhoulders and tears from his Eyes, for that he always ſuffered with thoſe who were ſufferers for Truths Teſtimony, and was often made willing to put his Shoulder under anothers burden, and hath often given eaſe to ſuch as were heavy loaden, by lending a hand of help; and though I had not the happineſs to be with him in the time of his Sickneſs, ſave only the ſpace of one hour the morning before he departed, in which time he often ſaid he had no trouble up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, although he was very weak, yet he walked ſeveral times o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſlower with me, and alſo a little out of door, ſaying, his peace far exceeded his pain, though he felt himſelf very weak, and in a few hours after he ſweetly departed this life, the tenth day of the fifth Month in the year <hi>1682.</hi> and is entred into everlaſting Joy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs with his God, and hath received an inheritance in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that ſhall never have end; where many who are yet in this body who have been refreſhed by him in his day, have true unity with his Spirit, and in remembrance of him can glorify and praiſe, and give thanks unto his God who is over all and worthy of praiſe and thansgiving for ever.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47206:3"/>
            <head>His Wives Teſtimony Concerning her Dear Husband, <hi>William Wilſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Living Teſt mony I have to give, Concerning my Dear Husband. He was a dear and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Husband over me, and that is the cauſe of my Sorrowing for the loſs of his outward Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; yet I can truely ſay, I have peace and true unity with his Spirit, as I ever had when we lived together. Bleſſed and praiſed be the Name of the Lord for evermore, who joyned us together in his Heavenly fear and pure unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted love, and was our guider on our way both inwardly and outwardly, and in that ſame love that the Lord joyned us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in, we lived in the ſame till the Lord was pleaſed to take him from me who is worthy of his own; although it be a hard Exerciſe to me many a time now in my old age to part with ſo Dear a Husband, but all is but a reaſonable ſacrifice for the Lord who is the preſerver of our Souls, that live in obedience unto his Will. And this I can truely ſay, and that to my great Comfort, that when the Lord was pleaſed to call him from me upon the Truths Account, whether in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> I never was his hindrance; but was freely willing to give him up to the ſervice that the Lord had called him unto, for I have often bidden him take no care for any thing he left behind, but have ſaid perform thy journey as thou ſees the Lord makes thy way; which I know he did and that with faithfulneſs, and that is his everlaſting joy, and my great comfort, though I be left behind him in this World; but my deſire and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eathing is to the Lord, to preſerve me and my two Daughters in his heavenly way to our lives end,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47206:4"/>as he did my dear Husband who laid down his body as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lamb, Saying, often times, I have not ſerved the Lord unfruitfully, and alſo ſaid I have no trouble upon me, and I am very ſenſible that all is well with him, for he was a peaceable man to the very latter end of his daies; Bleſſed and praiſed be the name of the Lord for evermore, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him unto his everlaſting joy and felicity for evermore</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>The 17th of the 11th. Month,</hi> 1682.</date>
               <signed>Dorothy Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>His Daughter <hi>Rebecca's</hi> Teſtimony concerning her Father.</head>
            <p>THis is my Teſtimony concerning my dear and well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Father <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> he was a dear and tender Father towards me, and that is the cauſe of my Shedding of tears many times, but it is not without hope; for I am Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with many more, who knew his Life and Converſation, that he is entred into everlaſting joy and felicity for evermore with his Maker. And this I can truly ſay to my daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he was a true director of Me and my Siſter on the Spiritual Journey even Sion wards, which he himſelf did tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel on dayly, and did bear a faithful Teſtimony for, to the end of his daies, both in <hi>England</hi> and other Nations; where the Lord was pleaſed to call him: tho through tryals and hardſhips, but he thought all little enough for the Lord and his holy truths ſake, Oh bleſſed and praiſed be the name of the Lord for evermore! for I can truly ſay my Father was raiſed up in a ſpiritual ſence towards us his Family, when he took his journey towards <hi>London;</hi> and in much tenderneſs exhorted us with tears, to keep in the true fear of the Lord that his name might be glorified by us, with many more good and heavenly Exortations to us on this manner, which was his laſt Teſtimony to us: for he lived but two nights and one day after he came home from <hi>London,</hi> and his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward body was much Spent, but he was in a Sweet and heavenly frame of Spirit, to his laſt breath; and often ſaid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47206:4"/>his peace was far above his pain. And ſo lay down his head in peace where none can make him afraid; Oh Lord God of Infinite love which hath broken my heart unto ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs before thee, thou haſt been a Husband to my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Father to Me and my Siſter! Oh Lord carry us on in thy heavenly way as thou didſt my Father, that thy name may be glorified by us in our little meaſures, for it is the deſire of my heart above all things to live in thy true fear that I may inherit the Crown of life as my Father doth! Bleſſed and praiſed be thy holy name for evermore ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>The 17th of the 11th Month,</hi> 82.</date>
               <signed>Rebecca Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>
               <hi>Ruth Wilſons</hi> Teſtimony concerning her Father.</head>
            <p>THis is my Teſtimony concerning my dear and faithful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> who was a dear and tender Father over me, which is the cauſe of my great lamentation when I heard of his deceaſe; for I was gone to <hi>Kendal</hi> to live, and did never ſee him alive after he took his Journey towards <hi>London,</hi> which was very hard for me to bear, and went near my very life, but in the Conſideration of his holy and pure life that he lived in, I am ſatisfied (with many that did know him) that he is in everlaſting Joy and Eternity. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and praiſed be the name of the Lord for ever, for he was ever inſtructing me on in that heavenly way that he himſelf travelled; into his latter end, and encouraging men in the way of the Lord often; ſaying, to my Siſter and Me, it would be the beſt portion that ever we could enjoy, which we know now to be very true. Bleſſed and praiſed be the name of the Lord for ever, who hath made us ſenſible wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of it in our little meaſures, and I deſire at the Lords hand that I with many more may be preſerved in the true fear of the Lord to my lacter end, for I know my dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did often travel in Spirit for us his family, when he was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47206:5"/>far ſeparated from us outwardly, ſometimes in his Journey upon truths account, and ſometimes in his impriſonment for conſcence ſake; and the Lord was with him in every need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full time, and now he was pleaſed to take him out of this troubleſome world, into his everlaſting joy, where he hath laid down his head in peace where none can make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; and the deſire of my heart is, that I with my Mother and Siſter may truely wait upon the Lord that we may know him to be as a Father unto the Fatherleſs, and as a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band unto the deſolate Widow, for he is a ſtrong Tower un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the upright in heart, and a ſure hiding place unto all his little ones; O bleſſed and praiſed be his Holy Name for ever and evermore, ſaith my Spirit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ruth Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>William Rawes <hi>his Teſtimony concerning</hi> Will. Wilſon.</head>
            <p>COncerning our dear friend and brother <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> I have this Teſtimony to bear for him in true remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him, he was a man of a Meek and quiet Spirit, which with the Lord is of great price; he had alſo a good gift to declare the truth, and was full of zeal and heavenly courage, in the which he perform'd the ſame. Alſo he was a good example and patern in his life and Converſation unto us, by the which he preached truth unto us, as well as by his words; for he himſelf lived according to what he taught us: for he was adorned with gravity, and walked before us in humility; yea, he had a blamleſs converſation and was unſpotted from the World, ſo that his preſence as well as his words, was a ſtrengthening and a comfort to the upright and honeſt-hearted, he was a man that did ſuffer much for truth's ſake, both impriſonment often, and ſpoil of goods which he took joyfully, knowing that in Heaven he had a better, and more enduring ſubſtance, he patiently endured all; ſaying, he had counted the coſt before he began to build, the Lord was his upholder in all hardſhips. And by his powerful
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47206:5"/>arm did ſupport him in all tryals and exerciſes that he met with, Bleſſed be the name of the Lord for ever, he did ſo worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walk in his life time obedient unto the grace of God, which appeared in his heart; that when it pleaſed the Lord to viſit him with ſickneſs, the Lord made it caſie unto him, that he many times did ſay, greater was his peace then his pain, peace did far out ballance his pain, and ſaid, I have not ſerved the Lord for nought, and very quietly took his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Saying, he was well contented whatſoever way the Lord was pleaſed, he was as a Dove harmleſs, and as a Lamb Innocent alſo waited he upon the Lord until his change did come: which when the time came, that he no longer might live in that Body, he prepared was to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, and an admittance into the Bridegroom's Chamber was found, where I know he is at reſt and peace for ever more with the Lord.</p>
            <div type="poem">
               <l>O Happy art thou dear William.</l>
               <l>Happy and Bleſſed of the Lord art thou for ever.</l>
               <l>Bleſſed art thou that is dead in the Lord.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt reſt from thy labour, and thy works do follow thee.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the Angels bright ſhall thou ſhine.</l>
               <l>In Heaven's joy to remain for ever.</l>
               <l>Where thou a Crown of life haſt obtained.</l>
               <l>A Diadem moſt, bright ſhalt thou wear.</l>
               <l>It was this thou laboured for here.</l>
               <l>It is obtained now by thee in Heaven where it was ſure there laid up for thee, till thou thy Teſtimony had finiſht.</l>
               <l>Now rejoyce thou dear friend and brother.</l>
               <l>In heaven's Glory ſhalt thou ſhine for ever.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Rawes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:47206:6"/>
            <head>Thomas Atkinſon <hi>his Teſtimony concerning</hi> Will. Wilſon</head>
            <p>ANd this ſame <hi>Will. Wilſon</hi> was a man indued with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and divine Knowledge, which the Lord had given him; and was made able to divide the word aright to every condition; he had milk for the babes to nouriſh them withal; and ſtronger food for men of ſtrength to go on with boldneſs, in the Lords work. And for temporal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs both for himſelf and others, who made uſe of him, he was ſo honeſt, true, and faithful in his dealings, that none could juſtly lay any thing to his charge; in this ſtate he both lived and dyed as to the World; but the remembrance of him will remaine for ages and generations yet to come, I had good experience of himſelf many years, and therefore I can give my Teſtimony for him, that he was an honeſt faithful man, although his body be gone the way of all fleſh.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Atkinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>William Walker <hi>his Teſtimony concerning</hi> Will. Wilſon.</head>
            <p>THis is my Teſtimony concerning my dear friend late deceaſed, which the Lord hath taken away from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; and is received into everlaſting reſt with the Father, where peace and joy is for evermore enjoyed. This Teſtimony I have to bear and to leave upon record for him this day, that his labour and travail was for the good of all, for he being one that often frequented my Fathers houſe, and he was made inſtrumental in the hand of the Lord, in that family when we were young in years for in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him, my heart, and ſoul, and ſpirit is even broken many times within me, ſo that many a time my Spirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but mourn within me, for want of ſuch a dear friend: though not as one without hope, being well ſatisfied that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47206:6"/>his ſoul is in everlaſting felicity, where true reſt and peace with the Lord for ever more.</p>
            <p>And further this Teſtimony I have to bear for him, that he was a man that was truely willing to labour with his hands in the creation, and that alwayes; a tender regard over his family, for this I can truely ſay, for him that it was his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt joy that his children ſhould be kept in the fear of the Lord, in which the living God hath had a regard to anſwer, for whom my Soul and Spirit on their behalf, can truely at this time give unto God the praiſe to whom all true praiſes belongs, for ever and for evermore, ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Walker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>Michael Wilſons <hi>Teſtimony concerning his Brother</hi> William Wilſon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WIlliam Wilſon</hi> being my natural Brother, and by trade a Taylor, and I when young being his Apprentice as well as his Brother, can in Reallity and truth give this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony concerning him, who before his convincement he was one that ſought the Lord to the utmoſt of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then, and for diſputing about the things of God and the Scriptures, he was behind few of the Profeſſors of thoſe times, and was one that walked as Circumſpectly as the moſt part of them did. Being zealous in his way yet ſtill ſome thing there was in him unſatisfied, which the Lord in his own due time did ſatisfie, and by his living and eternal power did raiſe to bear a Teſtimony for him, unto which Teſtimony vaiſed by the Lord in his heart; he was obedient and willing to be led and guided, which led him into the way of God, which is light, for Chriſt ſaid, who is the way to God, I am the light of the world, he that followeth me ſhall not abide in darkneſs but ſhall have the light of life. In which light he came to ſee that a profeſſion of the truth made not a Chriſtian, but a poſſeſſion of it; and alſo in it he came to ſee deceit both in Prieſts and Profeſſors, who talked of
<pb facs="tcp:47206:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47206:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47206:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47206:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47206:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47206:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:47206:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47206:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47206:11"/>the way of the Lord but walked in the way of error; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praying, and ſinging, for gifts and rewards; having more regard for the fleece then for the flock, ſeeking their gain from their Quarters, having lofty Spirits and proud and haughty looks, loving to go in long Robes that they may be taken notice of; ſitting in the higheſt Rooms of feaſts and having the Cheifeſt places in the Synagogues and loving ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the market places, and to be called maſter, even Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over people; againſt which my dear Friend and Brother was ſeveral times moved, by the living power of God to try and declare, and in his holy light did teſtifie againſt them, who had got on Sheeps Cloathing, but inwardly was Ravening wolves; for which he was cruelly handled at ſeveral Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, both by Prieſts and People; as for inſtance.</p>
            <p>When we went to work one time at a Houſe where was one <hi>Charles Crow</hi> a Prieſt, who came into the Room where we were working, who walked a while to and fro in the Room (with a Book in his hand ſomewhat larger then a pocket Bible) unto whom my Brother moderately ſaid, <hi>Charles,</hi> thou haſt a great toyl in getting thy leſſon, at which words the Prieſt in a rage came and took him by the hair of his head (where he was upon an high form, ſitting before the table) and pulled him down to the ground, panching him with his feet and knocking him on the head with the Book; which knocking ſome Women in another Room heard, and came at that time and prevented the Prieſt from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further harm.</p>
            <p>And alſo at another time being one feaſt day in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we were in his houſe at <hi>Langdal</hi> Chappel ſtile, who then felt the Lord to move upon his ſpirit that he ſhould go to <hi>Eſhdal</hi> Steeple houſe in the County of <hi>Cumberland</hi> (at which place he was Cruelly handled a few weekes, before by one Prieſt <hi>Parker</hi>) yet notwithſtanding he was willing to go (who witneſſed that ſaying my people ſhall be a willing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the day of my power, ſaid the Lord.)</p>
            <p>And we went from his houſe within a Quarter of the ninth hour, and we were in <hi>Eſhdal</hi> Steeple-houſe within a quarter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ten — between which places it being nine Miles and upwards of very rough way, and Prieſt <hi>Fogo</hi> being there,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47206:11"/>ſoon after we went in; he went into the Pulpit during which time my brother ſtood ſilent. And when he had done, my brother ſpoke ſome words to the people concerning the Prieſt, ſayings, and doings, which made the Prieſt to rage. And ſome of his hearers ſtanding up being officers, would have put my Brother forth; but the Prieſt ſaid, let him alone: then they ſat down again very willingly expecting to hear a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between them, but inſtead thereof the Prieſt came to him and took him by the Hair of his Head, and by the ſame pulled him to the ground, and drew him out of the Steeple-Houſe, while the Prieſt was thus exerciſed, I ſaid unto the people, mind the fruits of your Prieſt, the Scripture ſaith, lay violent hands on no man; which the Prieſt hearing came to me and in his rage and cruelty abuſed me in the beholding; of which acts of Cruelty done to us the people was many of them ſet againſt the Prieſt, which he perceiving got away home, and then my brother had good ſervice among the people a prety while, but within a few months after, the Prieſt met with a ſharp reproof for his Cruelty when he was riding over ſome ſands, accompanied with ſeveral people, he fell into a quick-ſand and was immediately drown'd, a juſt judgment of a perſecutor.</p>
            <p>And this in ſhort is a true Teſtimony of ſome of the fruits of the Prieſts; whom he in the light of the Lord went to reprove who made a great talk of Chriſt and Chriſtianity; yet notwithſtanding proved as Cruel as the beaſts of prey, tearing wolves though covered with lambs skin. And at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral houſes up and down the Country where we wrought, he met with many envious ſpirits who alſo were great talkers of God and Chriſt and the Scriptures, and the way to God; but walked in their own wills and wayes and would not bow nor bend unto Chriſt the light and way to God, they were climbed up ſo high in their imaginations, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelves in their ſelf righteouſneſs, and came forth in the ſtrength of the power of darkneſs to oppoſe the Truth and light of God which he bore Teſtimony unto; yet in the name of the Lord he ſtopped the mouths of many gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and in the wiſdom of. God that was with him he caught the wiſe and crafty in their own ſnare.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47206:12"/>
            <p>And in a holy zeal and heavenly courage, and living de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the ſpirit of truth, he declared the way of the Lord and his Exhortation was unto us, who in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure were turned to it, that we ſhould walk in the ſame; and in it watch againſt that dark Envious proud haughty Spirit which lay near to draw from it and to do well and keep low in Gods holy fear, and to deny our ſelves and take up the dayly Croſs to our own wills, and to be faithful in that little appearance of Light and Truth which we had already receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and then the Lord would make known more unto us whoſe words many of us now are come to witneſs, Bleſſed be the name of the Lord for evermore.</p>
            <p>And this Teſtimony I have to bear concerning my dear Brother, and it liveth in many and ſhall not dye, that he was an Innocent man and lived in the fear of God, and diligently ſought the Exaltation of his holy way; and his delight was to labour and travel that people might be gathered into the ſame and walk therein, that in their day and time they might be an honour unto God, for which end he made them, and they who in this age do declare for the ſame and ſeeks to worſhip him in his own ordained way, do meet with many hardſhips and cruel perſecutions as did the faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord in former ages; and as alſo did this inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent man. But the Lord was near unto him in every ſtrait, and was unto him a preſent help in every needful time, and in a living ſence of his eternal power, did in time of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs declare ſeveral ſweet and heavenly Exhortations; and alſo ſaying, I know it will be well with me: I have not ſerved the Lord for nought, his preſence I feel with me, and alſo ſaid my love is generally to friends; and ſtanding upon the floor between two Friends with difficulty of breathing, ſaid, Oh, that every one would mind the Lord that they might reap life, and then he ſat down and like a Harmleſs dove left this life; and ſo drew breath no more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:47206:12"/>
            <head>JOHN DIXON'S <hi>Teſtimony concerning</hi> William Willſon.</head>
            <p>I Being a Neighbour unto <hi>W. W.</hi> therefore have had a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledg of him, being many times converſant with him, though at the time of his Convincement I was but young in years; and before his Convincement when I learnt at School I had this knowledge of him, that in thoſe times he was one that diligently ſought the Lord to the utmoſt of his underſtanding; And that with the chiefeſt of profeſſors in thoſe times, he was one that took great pains in going from one profeſſing Prieſt to another, and for diſputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things of God and the Scriptures, was behind few of them. Yet ſtill there was ſomething unſatisfied in him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great and high profeſſion, then made untill his mind was turned to the Lord, who by his holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light and glorious power, did ſhine into his heart, by which Light he came to receive the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt Jeſus. And this Heavenly treaſure he had in his earthen veſſel, and willingly he attributed the excellency of the power thereof unto God, to whom it did belong being truely ſubject thereunto; for he was a man that had made ſelf then of little or no Reputation, therefore did the Lord exalt him and give him Wiſdom, Corage, and Boldneſs, and that in the ſight of his Enemies to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of them, and raiſing the witneſs of God in many.</p>
            <p>For ſoon after his Converſion, he was moved by the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of God, to cry againſt deceit, iniquity, oppreſſion, and tranſgreſſion, which abounded both in Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and was cruelly handled at ſeveral Steeple-houſes often by the Prieſts and ſometimes by the people for the Lord from whom nothing can be hid he knows, and many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel did ſee how that one Prieſt <hi>Parker</hi> of <hi>Eſhdal</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> becauſe this faithful and obedient ſervant by and through the Motion of the Divine Spirit of God; did
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47206:13"/>exhort people to mind that of God in their conſciences, and to turn to that holy Light and Law which he hath put in their inwards Parts; that by the ſame they might come to know the will of God and do it. I ſay, becauſe of theſe and ſuch like words the Prieſt in a cruel rage did beat and wound him, and with one of his Crutches did break his Head, and cauſed the blood to run down his Shoulders and Back; and being a lame man cauſed his Horſe to be brought, upon which he mounted, and in the ſight of the people did upon <hi>Williams</hi> bare head break his Staff in three pieces, which made the people cry fie upon ſuch mercileſs work. So when the Prieſt had made an end of his ſavage dealing, he ſet forwards to go home, but before he got thither he met with a reproof for his Cruelty, (from him who rewards every one according to the deeds done with body whether they be good or evil) for he ſtroak him with ſickneſs, ſo that he never came more at the Steeple-Houſe; during the time of which ſickneſs he was very loathſome, for he ſtinked above the ground, and was even made an example by him, who ſafely keeps his obedient ones from being devoured by the beaſis of Prey; who alone is worthy to be glorified for ever more.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Lord God of life, light, and power, who knows how to declare and to wrok both immediately and inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, who is never wanting unto his faithful and obedient Servants, who truly depend upon his holy divine Spirit; a meaſure of which he hath freely given to all mankind to be their inſtructer and leader into all Truth, and they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and for ever happy who are inſtructed and led thereby, and are truely and really given up thereunto, though they may meet with many difficulties and troubles as did this faithful Man, <hi>W. W.</hi> but out of them all the Lord delivered him, and in his holy power gave him dominion; and in the Authority of the ſame ſent him into <hi>Germany</hi> to bear a Teſtimony againſt the wickedneſs of the wicked, and againſt the ungodlineſs of the ungodly, warning the wicked to turn from his wicked wayes, and the ungodly from their ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts, unto the light of God in their hearts; and to the holy Meaſure of his divine Spirit in their inward parts,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47206:13"/>for which he ſuffered great hardſhip in the city of <hi>Hambrough,</hi> and in <hi>Germany</hi> and other places thereaways, both by Sea and by Land.</p>
            <p>And after he had finiſhed his ſervice which he had to bear for the Lord in thoſe parts, the God of Light brought him back again into his own native Country and outward habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, where he was a good inſtrument in the hand of the Lord, both to the gathering and incouraging of many in and to the way of the Lord, both in Declaration and alſo in life and Converſation. For as he taught ſo he lived in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity dread and fear before the Lord, being a good favour both in them that did believe, and alſo in them that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; reaching forth his hand daily for the good of all, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delighting in the way of the Lord, riſing early and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing late for the honour of the ſame, and durſt not bow, bend, nor honour, no haughty nor proud loſty mind: becauſe thereof he as well as many others of our dear friends have ſuffered great hardſhip, for they that fear the Lord know right well, and that by good experience its the humble that God teacheth, and he direct the meek and the lowly in the right way; which way our dear friend <hi>W. W.</hi> was very bold to declare unto many, and that in a living demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit of Truth, which is the moſt excellent teacher and teacheth to declare the way of God aright, for without a harkening and giving up to be led and guided by it. None can declare of the way of God aright, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their duty unto him, therefore its the concern of all to mind the meaſure or manifeſtation of the Spirit or grace of God, which is freely given to all that they may profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and thoſe that truly comes to profit therewith, they are often puſht at by them who do not mind it; inſomuch that is come to paſs in our day as it was in the day of the Prophet, he that now departs from iniquity, becomes a prey to them who rebel againſt the Light, Grace, or Spirit, of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And though this faithful warrier and ſervant of the Lord, did faithfully ſuffer perſecution in his own native Land near his outward habitation; yet ſtill the Lord preſerved him having more for him to go through, for it pleaſed the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47206:14"/>Lord to ſend him into <hi>Scotland</hi> ſeveral times there to declare his meſſage freely, which was, that God is light and in him is no Darkneſs at all; and ſo if poſſible to turn their minds from darkneſs to light, from <hi>Satans</hi> power unto the power of the Lord; unto which power every Soul ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and in the ſame to live and dwell and have their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſo ſhall it be well with them when the time comes that they muſt lay down this earthly Tabernacle, and muſt go hence and be no more ſin: for the Prophet ſaid, <hi>All fleſh is graſs and the glory of it, as the flower of the graſs withereth, and the flower thereof fadeth away,</hi> but the word of the Lord endureth for ever.</p>
            <p>And the laſt time that this faithful Souldier of Chriſt (who fought under his banner) was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> he was moved by the Spirit of the Lord to travel into the remote parts thereof (where many times he was in jeopardie of his life) there to declare unto them the way of the Lord freely, for freely he had received therfore freely he did give, as do all they Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt Jeſus who is come to learn of him, and to obey his command: who commanded his Miniſters, ſaying, <hi>freely ye have received freely give.</hi> And in theſe far and remote parts the Lord God of life and power (of whom he had freely received) was not a wanting unto him: but was a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help in every needful time, and was always neer to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his obedient traveller, until he had finiſhed his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which freely he had received from the Lord to bear in theſe remote places, and then the Lord God almighty of life and power, who was his leader thither, and his inſtructer there, was his protector back again: at whoſe coming his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Friends, and Neighbours was very glad; for though many had puſht at him and envied him, looking and often expecting for his ruin and Inpriſonment, ſeveral of them did then ſtand in need of him, for the Lord bleſt his labour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way, and made him able and willing to help them in ſeveral of their neceſſities; for his hand was alwayes open to the needful, and his delight was to do good to them that had done ill to him, for indeed he overcame evil with that which was good. So that they that formerly had been his enemies, was made to ſay <hi>William Wilſon</hi> is an honeſt Man, for he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47206:14"/>walked circumſpectly as thoſe that are redeemed by the Lord, ſeeking by all means to bring honour to the way of the Lord and to exalt the ſame over all the by-ways ſet up in the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len wiſdom of man for the way of the Lord is a ſpiritual way, and his worſhip a ſpiritual worſhip; for all that truly worſhips him, it muſt be in Spirit and in Truth. And not in forms traditions and outward obſervations, as loe hear and loe there in this tradition; and that obſervation which many have made a great ſtir about, and been fitting up in their own wills and ways, being degenerated from the Spirit of the Lord in which he is only alone worſhipped.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this faithful ſervant and Miniſter of the Lord did often cry againſt thoſe that taught for Doctrine the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men, being ignorant of the cammand of the Lord in themſelves, therefore he was often by them haled to priſon and Cruelly handled as was hinted before. And ſeveral times ſued for tythe, for <hi>John Ambroſs</hi> in the year 1682. did exhibit a bill in the Exchequer againſt him and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other of his friends, becauſe they could not give him tythe for his cure, who in his bill of complaint to the ſaid court affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he was their Curate; but it hath pleaſed the Lord to provide a better place for him. Then <hi>John Ambroſs</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or ſought for him, for his intentions was (if his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable ends was not anſwered) to put him in ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or dungeon, or ſuch like place, or elſe to ruinate him in his eſtate; and ſo its come to paſs in our day and we are living witneſſes of the words of the Prophet of the Lord, concerning thoſe that deceive people, and cauſed them to err and bite with their Teeth; and cry peace, and he that putteth not into their mouths they even prepare war againſt him, <hi>Micah.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>And this is that cure they Miniſter unto thoſe who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put into their Mouths, who in the light of the Lord hath ſeen their deceit, and can in reality and truth give this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Teſtimony that they are Curates of no value, for thoſe that have been feeding ſuch Curates, and have been living under their cure Twenty, Thirty, Forty, or Fifty Years; many of them hath as great reaſon to cry at this day, as they had the firſt day they went to them, no Health in us, no Health in us.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47206:15"/>
            <p>And therefore all hath great need to walk in the ſpirit of the Lord, that in the ſame they may pray unto him, and ſay, from ſuch Biters, Preparers of War, and Curates, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from ſuch Curates, God almighty hath delivered his faithful ſervant <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> and placed him where they cannot touch him with their War, nor come near him with all their ſharp Inſtruments, nor wound him with their Darts, nor bruiſe him with their Blowes. The good Curate who freely gives his Cure, who is indeed a Phiſicion of value, who heals all that come unto him and doth depend upon him; he alone hath taken care for him and given him reſt from his labours, for the Lord hath an eye to them that have an eye to him, and he draws near to them that draws near to him; and he is a true preſerver of them that depend upon him and ſingly deſire to walk in his way. Which way this faithful man <hi>William Wilſon</hi> had a tender regard unto, who above all things deſired that he might be preſerved in the ſame, and be in his day and time an honour to the ſame, and in reality and truth ſo he was; and for it he had a delight day and night to labour and travel, and was in his journey and travel for the renown of the ſame, when the Lord of life and power was pleaſed to viſit him with ſickneſs, which he took very patiently earneſtly; deſiring of the Lord to turn him which way he thought beſt, and to bring him to his Wife and Children.</p>
            <p>And according to his deſire, God almighty whom he ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in reality of heart, who had been with his ſaithful travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and delivered him in many ſtraits and dangers, was at this time near unto him, and ſtrengthen his outward man (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he deſired) and brought him to his Wife and Children and outward habitation, where ſeveral came to viſit him, unto whom he ſaid, it will be well with me what way ſoever the Lord be pleaſed to order me. And the third day after he came home he was taken out of the Body, dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which time he ſet his Houſe in order, and ſeveral ſweet and Heavenly exhortations he left among his Familly, and within half an hour before his departure he walked over the Floor between another Friend and me, who ſaid, my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47206:15"/>love is generally to Friends, and then after a little ſpace with great difficulty of breathing he uttered theſe expreſſions, Oh, that every one would mind the Lord that they might reap life, which being ſpoken like a harmleſs Dove, he ſat down in his Chair and ſoon after drew breath no more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>William Rigg's <hi>Teſtimony Concerning</hi> William Wilſon.</head>
            <p>THis teſtimony have I to give for our dear Friend <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> that he was an innocent Man; a lover of truth and righteouſneſs, and not only ſo, but a walker therein for by his honeſt and upright life and Converſation, he was a preacher of righteouſneſs unto many as well as by Word and Doctrine, which he was a labourer in for many years; not only in this Land but in more remote parts of the World beyond the Sea; and the Lord was with him, and his power and preſence did go along with him: and the Lord made him inſtrumental in his hand for the good of many, for it was the joy of his heart to ſee truth proſper, and that many might come to enjoy that precious Pearl and Jewel of great worth the Kingdom of God in them, which conſiſteth in Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt which he was made a living witneſs of. And his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony was living and powerful to the teaching of the witneſs of God in many, not only by word and Doctrine, but alſo by life and Converſation, (as I ſaid before) whereby he reached the beſt part in all Men with whom he was Concerned, or where ever he was ordered to go, ſo that all were forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he was an honeſt Man, for he was of a lowly, meek, and Condeſcending Spirit unto the meaneſt Capacities whereby he got the love of many, and he confirmed and ſcaled his Teſtimony not only by doing uprightly, but alſo by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpoiling of his goods and impriſonment of his body, and alſo by blowes, wounds, and cruel uſage by inhumane and unreaſonable Men, counting nothing too hard to ſuffer for the teſtimony of Jeſus, and for the love of him who had ſatisfied his Soul, he was ſeeking the truth in its purity and glory which he did receive, and did continue faithful to the Lord in what he had received of him, even until the day of his departure out of the body, ſo that his memorial is bleſſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47206:16"/>and he hath left a ſweet ſmelling ſavour behind him, and the ſweet unity of his life, and the bleſſed fellowſhip of his Spirit lives and remains with us; and as he lived an innocent life ſo was his latter end comfortable. It was not my happineſs to ſee him in his ſickneſs, yet I had the Relation by ſeveral honeſt Friends that he was in a ſweet and heavenly frame of Spirit, and when he was asked how he did, he would have ſaid he was well, for my pain ſaid be cannot mount ſo high but my peace is above it; but I hope further account of this will be given by ſome that were eye and ear witneſſes, well, tho his body be gone to its place and his Spirit to God that gave it, and is entered into his reſt with the Lord, and is Crowned with an immortal Crown of life and glory which was laid up for him, and not for him only, but for all them that love the appearance of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, yet the unity of his life lives in my heart and I have fellowſhip with him in Spirit; and even at the time of the writing of this Teſtimony, my heart is made glad: and my Soul is ſweetly refreſhed in the remembrance of the bleſſed ſeaſons which we have had together, for many of them is freſh in my remembrance, and I do remember his Exhortation was often to Friends to keep in the unity of the Spirit; for ſaid he, it is of a longer extent then we, it will live and remain when we are gone, of the truth of which I am made a living Witneſs glory to God for ever. And ſo I deſire unto the Lord God of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs and Truth, that all the gathered ſheep of my Heavenly Fathers fold, may be preſerved from the Ravenous Beaſts of Prey; and that we my all be kept faithful in our Teſtimony for the Lord, while we have a day that we may lye down our heads in peace with the Lord; as do I ſtedfaſtly believe our dear Friend and Brother <hi>William Wilſon</hi> hath done.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By a lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs, William Rigg.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:47206:16"/>
            <head>James Pask<hi>'s Teſtimony concerning</hi> William Wilſon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WIlliam Wilſon</hi> was truly a Man of God who did much good, and was a Pillar in the Houſe of God in his Generation; he did not gad abroad to change his way, or go out from the pure way of God: but ſtedfaſtly keep and walked in it all his dayes after he came to know it, he was a man of love to God, and his people that is good, and knew well how to chuſe the good and refuſe the evil; unblamable in holineſs and ſerved the living and true God ſaithfully, his reſt is glorious, and his reward great in Heaven with the Lord God and the Lamb for ever and ever. For his labour of love and ſervice in the Church of God, which very much he deſired the welfare and proſperity of, he overcome by the blood of the lamb, and the word of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony which he held who loved not his life to the death. I cannot but think of him and lament for the Churches loſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, of ſuch a tender overſeer of ſuch a Friend and ſaithful Brother; and for his Widow and Childrens loſs of ſuch a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Father ſo careful for their good, ſo loving and tender to them: I deſire they all may be contented and reſt ſatisfied in the will of the Lord; in which he is gone to his eternal reſt from us all as to viſible appearance, but that ſpirit of God in which he walked, ſtill we enjoy to our great comfort in all our tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, I knew him well Five and Twenty Years, he was ever very dear and near to me; we travelled through <hi>Scotland</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many years ſince, where we patiently endured what exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, perils, and troubles we then met with; having a good and Eſtectual ſervice for the Lord God in that Nation which after we had truly performed, we returned in peace and Gods favour. In the pure love of God was I moved to give this Teſtimony on the behalf of this my late dear Brother, and companion in the work of the Lord; who is fallen aſleep and taken up his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt in Chriſt Jeſus who lives and Reigns for ever and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Pask</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:47206:17"/>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <p>
               <hi>WILLIAM WILSON</hi> was arreſted with ſeveral more of his Friends, and had before Juſtice <hi>Fleeming,</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Kirby,</hi> only for meeting together in Gods name and fear, for which he the ſaid <hi>W. W.</hi> with ſeveral other friends was ſent to <hi>Lancaſter-Caſtle</hi> where he had the Oath of Alleagance tendered to him, upon the refuſal of which he was ſent to priſon again, and there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral months, who ſoon after the Aſſizes (his fidelity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made known to the King) was releaſed and ſet free from that bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> who for conſcience ſake could not pay Six pence or Seven pence a year to Prieſt <hi>Ambroſs,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Grovenor;</hi> was by him ſued in the Exchequer court and run to a writ of Rebellion, and by vertue of the ſame areſted and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon ſeveral Months, during which time he wrote ſeveral let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Dorothy</hi> his Wife, and Friends, Coppies of ſome of them is as followeth.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>Dear Wife, I received thine from <hi>Ambleſide,</hi> and hath heard of thee ſince by <hi>B. B.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> and its ſatisfaction to me that I hear of thine and my Childrens Health and wellfare. And I long to ſee that opportunity that thou might come to ſee me, but dear Wife, I do not at all deſire it till thou canſt well, for Alas! I know that thou hath over much travelling up and down about thy needful affairs; but the Lord will order as he ſees good, and all will be well in his due time: we have had true experience of Gods love to us, and therefore we may ſpeak, for we can tell of his goodneſs towards us, and may believe in the ſame. For there is no doubtfulneſs in our cauſe, for he knoweth our hearts and the end of all our doings and ſufferings, and therefore he will deliver in his ſeaſon and that is to be waited for with us all, thee and me and all that knows the Lord, for he that will not ſpare to reprove Kings for the ſakes of his anointed, of which anointing we have all received a meaſure of, he will not ſpare an old Hireling Prieſt who are in the ſteps of following after the wages of unrighteouſneſs, and greedily ſeeking his Prey, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven devouring the poor if it were poſſible; will not the Lord hear for the ſake of his own? Ye, he will hear and be revenged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the ſake of his dearly beloved and Anointed, whom the Devil nor all Agents can never prevail againſt the Lord, vvill
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47206:17"/>hear the cry of his own and plead the cauſe of the innocent, and releaſe the diſtreſſed, and ſet his own life and power at liberty; which lies groaning under the burden of oppreſſion, where it muſt not lye, the Lord hath ſpoken and therefore he will deliver, he hath ſtriken and he will ſtrike, and by his ſtrokes we are healed; he hath wrought, and he will work and who can hinder: if the wicked have his prey for his ſeaſon, yet the Lord will bring him to his end; but Gods proſperity and truth ſhall never have an end neither in this World nor in the World to come.</p>
               <p>Therefore my dear and loving Wife, whom God hath given me and not man, we may well be content and waite with much patience the Lords time in all things, knowing that it hath been our beſt time; we can never call to mind the things that are paſt ſince we knew this truth of God, but we have had comfort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and I can never deſire it otherwiſe if I ſhould be reſtrained of the liberty of my body all the dayes of my life.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine <hi>W. W.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear and loving Wife</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have nothing to write unto thee as yet, but only the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my unfained love unto thee and my Children, hoping you are in Health as I am at this preeſnt I praiſe the Lord of Heaven and Earth, for it is reaſonable well with me every way I bleſs the Lord for it, and deſire to know how it is with thee; tho indeed it goes near me to ask how things is with thee, becauſe I cannot help thee; and that is my heavineſs ſometimes. But the Lord will in due time plead my Innocent cauſe who knows the uprightneſs of my heart; and that one hair of my head ſhall not uphold the falſe profits wayes nor the hirelings wages, who ſaith and doth not, I have been often aſſaulted to have it payed for me, but my uprighteouſneſs is known to the Lord and I cannot diſſemble with my God, but this is a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to the World, and therefore they cannot receive it but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee my loving Wife is it given to underſtand. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I much comforted, and the Lord preſerve thee and my little Children in the true fear of God, for our way is not to look
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47206:18"/>out, and therefore I can inwardly beſeech the Lord for you all, thy dear and loving Husband, <hi>W. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>My love to all our Family</hi> Kendal <date>
                     <hi>the 14th of the 10th Month,</hi> 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Will. Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>My Dear Friends and Brethren, who are like to be fellow ſufferers with me in this caſe, of not yielding to ſatisfie the will of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable man; who is perſecuting us for not paying him tythes or reckonings as he calls them.</head>
            <p>TO all you my faithful Friends, this is the word of advice unto you all, that you ſee and examine your ſelves well, and ſee how ye ſtand in Gods righteouſneſs; that ſo my Dear Friends your ſufferings may never become your burden, but that your eſtabliſhment may be felt in Gods Righteouſneſs with you all; for my friends, you had better never have put your hand to this plow then to look back, therefore my friends examine well your own ſelves, how you are minded in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, for the Lord knows my heart. I wiſh you all well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the honour of Gods truth as mine own heart, and therefore I would not have any of you all to go one ſtep further then you feel the ſuffering ſeed of God Almighty, to bear you up in your pure bleſſed minds that ſees over all the ſufferings that can happen in this preſent world. For indeed Friends, in this eſtate God will plead our cauſe and our ſuffering with him, will bring a raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, and in this ſtate friends you muſt look over Wife and Children which is near and dear unto you all, but Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is more then all and will bear you out over all and through all, for the Lord alone will be your help, and no man ſhall need to plead our cauſe, but he will appear for us in his due time, when he ſaith it is enough, who ſhall be able to ſay Nay. Therefore my friends feel your hearts, purified from all double mindedneſs that ſingle in God righteouſneſs, you may be found and ſo will his holy ſeed reign in your hearts, and Gods bleſſing will be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Children, that ſo you need not fear the want of any good thing unto them nor your Wifes the beloved of your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47206:18"/>under God; and therefore Friends in ſingleneſs of heart, as having a ſence of your Conditions, I write theſe lines unto you for the bettering of your eſtabliſhment in Gods Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where you will never be made afraid to appear for the Lord; and bear a ſingle Teſtimony for his name and truth upon Earth, for truly Friends, this is the feeling of my heart, and the full bent of my mind, that if one hair of my head would ſerve in conſideration of this task, I could not give it, I believe I ſhall not be a Hypocrite; I would not be found out of Gods Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs doing mine own will, but even the will of him that hath called me that his power might be more made manifeſt. And therefore friends, was this word of Exhortation the more in my heart unto you all, that you might truly feel your own ſelves in that which will carry through, or elſe as I ſaid it were better never to ſtep further then to faint by the way, but hoping you are furniſhed with that heavenly ſpirit of life, that will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry through to the end as need requries; I take leave with you all and reſt your loving Brother</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>And Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LOok not back into <hi>Aegypt</hi> for help, for it is in vain, neither have we need ſo to do; for the Lord is our helper therefore we need not fear what man can do unto us; for Friends, I dare not look out at any thing of any hand, for if I do I am afraid, and Gods witneſs would be againſt me, and would be heavier then a thouſand ſuch as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> the Prieſt could be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you eye and mind the Lord above all hireling Prieſts, is the advice of your Friend and Brother.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Will. Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:47206:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>William Wilſon</hi> being moved of and by the living power of God to travel into the <hi>North,</hi> or remote parts of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to declare what the Lord did then; and there immediately reveal unto him, during the time of which travail he wrote ſeveral letters into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to his Wife, Coppies of which is as followeth.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Wife,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN the living truth of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, doth the bowels of my unſained love, ſalute thee in the unſeparable life, doth my deareſt love reach unto thee in the unchangeable life of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where we cannot forget each other; dear heart my life is often powred out before the Lord in conſideration of thee my dear love, the Lord thy God who hath ſeperated the from thy Mothers womb, and hath in meaſure brought thee to be of the womb of eternity; where thou mayeſt feel the inviſible ſence of Gods eternal love towards thee and thy Dear Children, and he cannot forget his own that is without queſtion. Canſt thou forget the Children of thy Womb? its poſſible thou may, but the Lord cannot forget his Children whom he hath called to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all and follow him; his dayly bleſſings cannot but attend ſuch every day that comes over their heads. Dear love, My life is with thee in the Lords preſence, but my Body is at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> at this preſent with the. My good Friends, where I feel their care is over me, and my companion that walks with me, Oh pray that we may walk worthy, or elſe all is in vain! O we have need to be watchful againſt that old nature that would be ready to leaven into the old lump again! and reckon that Gods Truth may be holden there; but it is not ſo, our God is of purer eyes then to behold iniquity, it is the old man muſt be put off, and Chriſt Jeſus the new man muſt be put on which followeth after Righteouſneſs. And this is that alone that ſeaſons our hearts with grace, and preſerves our minds in his fear and in his true love we are kept; which loves one another and thinks no evil but bears one another in love, exhorts one another in love, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into unity one with another, that the Devil cannot get any power to hurt or ſcatter us from God nor one from another, and in this are we known to be of God, if we love one another: that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47206:19"/>ſo God who for Chriſts ſake hath ſhewed his love unto you, may be glorified and honoured by you. And thus much at preſent I feel to write unto you, even the Lord Love that is large unto us, that our dayly prayers may be to be kept in it to his glory and praiſe for ever; <hi>my dear Wife,</hi> thou knowſt my love is dear unto Friends, thou muſt let it be ſo remembred unto all our Meeting; <hi>Dear Wife,</hi> I ſay little of my return as yet, but the Lords will be done, that is my whole deſire; for I am many miles from the end of my Journey, whether I hope I ſhall attain unto in Gods time: I am not haſty but rather deſires to be of uſe or ſervice amongſt Friends as I go. For this firſt day I hope to be at <hi>Allan,</hi> at a meeting where many hath of late as they ſay have a deſire to hear, it is about twelve miles beyond <hi>Aberdeen;</hi> on the third day after a meeting of Friends at another place, and then on my journey as God makes way and, in the mean time think it not long, but ſolace thy ſelf in the ſingleneſs of heart with the Lord, who will ever be as an Husband unto thee, and to my Children as a Father; and inperfect ſenſe of the ſame, and in dear love with thee and all men living upon Earth. I take leave with thee, and reſt and remain thine in the Lord while I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Wilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Aberdeen</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> 
                     <date>the 25th of the 5th Month, <hi>1673.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Now my dear and loving Wife,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Can write ſome encouraging lines unto thee, whereby I hope to the Lord that ſent me away from thee, that by his powerful aſſiſtance I may ſee thee again ere it be long; for the Lord hath pleaſed to ſet me as free from the <hi>North</hi> end of <hi>Scotland</hi> to come home again to thee and my Children, as he did ſet me free from you to God, and did viſit his ſeed in that remote part of the Earth, and the Iſles thereabout: where his witneſs lies ſlain in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, though not wholly dead in others though in great bondage; but the Lords power is the ſame there as it was with us at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; and he is able to raiſe up even thoſe that are dead, and bring to life thoſe that are ſtaggering: and releaſe his own out of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47206:20"/>Captivity though it may ſeem to be through many ſtraits, and difficulties, his arm is not ſhortned, and it muſt be ſtretched forth to his own praiſe. <hi>Dear Wife,</hi> it is fourteen years ſince a Friend was here amongſt this people, and as I ſaid unto thee, it was the very day and time for me to go, as thou knowſt I ſaid unto thee before I left thee. I could not deferr the time any longer, for this was the very year and time, and I was the man that was to go; and ſo <hi>dear Wife</hi> having accompliſhed my end in the name of God, I can return in great peace, for at this preſent I feel no other; for my end in all things is Gods Glory and my Souls Peace, as thou knows right well, I have never ſought my ſelf in thoſe things, and ſo as I ſaw afore hand hath much come to paſs, for my part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as I ſaid to thee when I ſpoke through Faith was ſuch a one as feared not the face of any man that did appear againſt God, and we have ſound of all ſorts, but the Lords bleſſed truth was ſet over all heads, and all Prieſts and people: we need not much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late that now. And I have been pretty well preſerved in Health on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a little in the Iſle of <hi>Stromy</hi> I was aguiſh a little, but I kept over it as well as I could, and mended again in three or four dayes. I have thought often, O that I had but one word how thou were and my Children! but I ſee not how that can be, and therefore I can wiſh in pationce, hoping all is well. <hi>Dear Wife,</hi> I have written to thee ſince I came from home ſix times before this, whether thou have received them or not; the laſt was from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdeen</hi> ſix weeks before this, but I can ſay little of writing more before I come, though it may be a month or more yet, or I can get home if all be well: but as to that I leave it to the Lord, thou mayſt be glad that the Lord hath preſerved us amongſt the unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Generation, and ſet us ſafe again amongſt them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
               <p>I hear that dear <hi>G. F.</hi> is come again into <hi>England,</hi> my heart is glad of the happy return; let my dear love be minded to all Friends in General of all meetings round about as thou lights with any of them, thou muſt not expect my coming haſtily or I cannot travel hard, but I am very well both as to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mind, if any write to <hi>London</hi> let me be minded to our Friends that went to <hi>London,</hi> ſo with my love that never chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>from <hi>Awbonthy</hi> 
                     <date>the 5th day of the 7th month in <hi>Scotland,</hi> 1673.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>W. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:47206:20"/>
            <head>A Coppy of an Account of ſome of the ſufferings of <hi>William Wilſon</hi> (which account was found amongſt his Papers written with his own hands) ſince the Reſtoration of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the <hi>II</hi> as followeth.</head>
            <p>IN the year 1660 on the <hi>22th</hi> day of the <hi>7th</hi> Month; I was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted with a Warrant from Juſtice <hi>Braithwait</hi> of <hi>Ambleſide,</hi> by <hi>T. D.</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Langdal</hi> upon information made by <hi>John Tomſon</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Graſmire</hi> in <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> for ſpeaking ſome words to the people in Gods fear, and bidding them mind their teacher, ſo at the next Seſſions I was fined by Juſtice <hi>Fleeming</hi> and the reſt of the Juſtices in one hundred Marks, and committed into the Goal at <hi>Kindal</hi> until payment was made, as the tenure of the Mittimus did run; and ſo remaining in priſon a while until the firſt Seſſions next after. At which time the ſame Juſtices ſent for me, who tendered me the Oath of Allegiance, and becauſe for Conſcience ſake I could not ſwear, was ſent to priſon again, there to remain till I took the Oath and paid the fine of an hundred Marks as aforeſaid, although in the year 1648. I had ſuffered the loſs of all I had (ſaving my life) for the King as I made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, yet I remained in priſon above half a year, and then was ſet free by the Kings act of indulgence.</p>
            <p>In the year 1662. in the <hi>10th</hi> month I was committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> with many more of my Friends by War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from Juſtice <hi>Fleeming</hi> and <hi>William Kirby,</hi> for meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth; where at the next following Seſſions, I had the Oath tendered me again by theſe ſaid Juſtices and others; and becauſe I durſt not ſwear, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon where I remained Twenty weeks.</p>
            <p>In the year 1665. I was arreſted by warrant from Juſtice <hi>Fleem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Braithwait,</hi> for meeting with my Friends the <hi>5th</hi> of the <hi>9th</hi> Month at the houſe of <hi>Reignal Holme</hi> for which I was impriſoned one Month in <hi>Kendal,</hi> in the year 1670. I was fined in twenty pounds by vertue of an act made to prevent Seditious Conventicles by Juſtice <hi>Fleeming</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Phillipſon,</hi> for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few words of Truth in ſoberneſs in our peaceable meeting (to Juſtice <hi>Phillipſons</hi> man who was turned informer) for which I had taken from me two Cows worth five pound, one Horſe worth forty Shillings, and Oate meal worth ten Shillings.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:47206:21"/>
            <p>And again, for ſpeaking in a meeting at <hi>Fieldhead</hi> near <hi>Hanks-head,</hi> I was fined in twenty pounds for which my goods was ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>William Satterthwait</hi> Conſtable, <hi>James Harriſon</hi> Warden, and <hi>William Groves</hi> overſeer, all of <hi>Landal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1673. for not paying ſix pence or ſeven pence in the year to Parſon <hi>Ambroſs</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Graſmire</hi> for tythe, I was arreſted with an Exchequer proceſs, called a commiſſion of Rebellion and caſt into Priſon at <hi>Kendal,</hi> where I continued ſixteen weeks and then ſet free by the Goaler, being three weeks after the writ was not of date.</p>
            <p>But theſe are ſmall matters, in conſideration of what the God of my Life hath led one through ſince I knew his glorious Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King came in; for many a time have I ſuffered cruel Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Stackings, Stoneing, Buffitings, Beatings, and Knockings by the hirelings, Prieſts and rude People; and all for deſiring the good of their Souls, and that they might turn to the God of Light in whom there is no darkneſs at all, and ſo come out of darkneſs that they might have the light of life,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Wolſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>An Epiſtle General, or a token of my Love and care in my meaſure of the Heavenly Father of Glory, of Peace and of Love to all friends in their meetings, as it is Judged meet and Convenient to be read.</head>
            <p>IN the grace of God and love of the heavenly Father which hath viſited us in this acceptable day, of his abounding mercy I greet you all, in the Virgine love and ſtate of the pure Church of God which he hath called and gathered together in our day and age, glory to his Name for ever: who hath found us worthy to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame; and his eternal love and tender merties it even unto us day by day, and time after time, in our heavenly Meetings, which he hath gathered us into, that we may wait upon him in, and think upon his Holy Name. Bleſſed for ever be his name, he hath ſet us in a holy ſtate and brought us into a deep ſence of his pure love which runs freely among us from day to day, and keeps all the careful and upright in heart unto himſelf; and they glorifie his holy name, and all the careleſs and diſordered perſons doth diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our his moſt holy and bleſſed Name, and this will be their ſhame
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47206:21"/>and great condemnation. But the glory of the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall be revealed in the upright hearted, and carefully minded Men, and Women, Sons, and Daughters, of the preclous life and ſeed of God, which is riſen amongſt us in this our day and time of Gods love and heavenly viſitations unto us, who keeps the good order and ſtate of the pure Church; but unto them who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belle againſt the ſpirit and regards not the good order and ſtate of the pure Church; unto ſuch will the Lord appear and be angry with them if they do not amond, and have a greater regard unto his moſt Holy Name and Place and Spirit; which would cauſe them not to err not depart from the good order and Spirit of God unto the which they are called, therefore my Friends, Brethren, and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in the name of the Lord of Hoſts, I charge and warn you all, that you keep to that of God in you all, and that will keep you all in the remembrance of the beginning, and let you all ſee the good order and ſtate of the true Church, in God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God the light of the World; in whom we are all to walk, to move, and have our being. So remember my Friends, how careful you all were at the firſt, and tender at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; and troubled at that which was out of order, and your Spirits grieved and could not well bear the things that ſome will now allow, and be ready in defence thereof to ſay, Alas! Friends were weak at the firſt, but we are more able to hear or to bear things now, which were a great offence or trouble then; Alas! my friends the Lord was near unto us then, and did uphold us in our weakneſs, and was with us in all out undergoings, and did uphold us on every hand; and none could open their Mouths againſt his harmleſs Lambs, but the Lord was ſufficient in them to ſhut it again. But now my Friends, they have many things to lay to the charge of ſome Friends who frequently comes to our Meetings, and yet they find them in the Cuſtoms of the World, (and not after Chriſt) yea in very blameable and moſt reproveable faſhions of the world, which the Apoſtle forbids, and ſaith, <hi>Faſhion not your ſelves like unto this world, for the Faſhions thereof paſſeth away;</hi> and ſome in being too conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in drinking too much at Ale-Houſes, and taking of Tobacco a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, which is an evil ſavour unto the Lord, and that which your Spirits could not bear at the firſt. Alas! Friends have you loſt your firſt love, or is your tender zeal departed from you; and alſo the common payment of tythes or ſuch like dues ſo called is to much upheld among ſome of you; which all is convinced of to be Jewiſh and Antichriſtian, and many of our dear Friends that ſuffer for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47206:22"/>not paying of them is occaſioned the more to ſuffer, though the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs of thoſe who do pay, or ſuffer it to be done, as they in all parts of the Nation, who gathers tythes is ready to blaſh poor harmleſs Friends in the face with; and this is one thing the Lord is greatly offended with, who is able to preſerve uphold and deliver the faithful (and yet all go under his name this doth occaſion his grief) and furthermore my Friends the Lord is grieved with ſome. Slackening their Zeal in your Meetings, and being ſo heaviſome when you are met together to wait upon the Lord, then do ſome let in the careleſs mind, and ſo loſes their pure zeal; and deadneſs and drowſineſs comesover and burdens the ſeed of God in others, and doth hurt in your Meetings, and occaſions the world to open their Mouths againſt us; and this is a great evil, and doth cauſe the Lord to be angry with us, and is pitiful over thoſe that ſuffers by them. And this is out of the good order and ſtate of the true Church, and a great ſpot in ſome families; Oh Friends! Have you not Houſes to eat and to drink in, and are they not alſo to ſleep in? Oh my Friends! think of thoſe things, it is Gods free love to you to tell you of your faults, who is found faulty herein; that thereby you may amend and renew your ſtrength in the Lord, who is able to give you ſtrength and power over all theſe things, and will do it to all who is willing and obedient to the croſs of Chriſt. Oh my Friends! I cannot forbear but I muſt tell you of one thing, which as I thought I was in a Meeting, and as I thought we were but heaviſome and not as we ſhould all of us have been, and there was among us as little Child of about ſix years old, and ſhe began to cry and weep bitterly, yea very ſore, and I did behold the little Child, and I ſaw that here weeping was of God, and ſhe cryed ſore, ſo that I prayed earneſtly to God in my heart, for the little Child that ſhe might ſpeak if ought troubled her Spirit concerning Gods Church and People; and immediately the little Child ſpoke and ſaid, <hi>Friends ſhould not ſleep in their Meetings,</hi> and immediatly I awoak and ſaw the ſtate of the true Church and the diſorder that was among Friends, and the little Child was a Virgin and in the ſtate of the true Church, and without ſpot and blameleſs in the ſight of God; the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is able to preſent us all perfect without ſpot or wrinkle in the ſight of our God, who hath called us all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and newneſs of life, in which the Lord God of Eternal life keep you all my Friends, Brethren, and Siſters in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Brother in my meaſure of God W. W</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:47206:22"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to Friends of <hi>Haukeſhead</hi> Meeting.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends, Brethren and Siſters in the Church of the firſt born, and of the Royal Seed of the moſt high God, grace, mercy, and peace be multiplyed among you, to whom God hath revealed what he hath determined and is now manifeſting in this day of his power, that every one of you in the Light and life might ſtand ſingle, out and over the ſnares of thoſe whom God is laying aſide as the broken reeds of <hi>Aegrpt;</hi> that his own name might be truſted in, and his mighty arm alone felt and ſeen in leading and preſerving his people to his Glory. Oh! my Friends my deſire is much for you, that you be kept faithful in the Lord. Oh! I ſay that I am glad when I read you near me in the life of God, a top of all this world and its Wayes, and its Love, and Fellowſhip, and Faſhions, and Cuſtoms which all, periſh with the uſing; but my Friends dwell in that which ſeperates and puts a difference between you and the World; to wit, the light that Judges the World, and hath given you clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſee the juſt Condemnation of the World becauſe of its evil deeds. So let your Fellowſhip be in the Light my Dear Friends, and live dear and near one with another and one to another, that ſo the world by you dayly may be judged, and feel your dayly Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration from any thing that you ſee to be evil; and be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by any means of fleſhly reaſoning or conſultation with fleſh and blood, which cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, but draws out into the Kingdom of this World; and ſo breads your peace with God. Oh! my Friends feel dayly your clearing up by the Truth, and your freedom from the in tanglements of the World, that you may feel how the Lord doth ſet you upon his moſt holy Hill, that you may ſhine as lights unto the World. For this end hath the Lord called and choſen us that we may dwell and abide in his Light, and ſhew forth his praiſe unto the World; and his glorious works unto the ends of the Earth. And I may ſay again I am with you in the Lord, whom I feel and find faithful: my life is raiſed with you out of the duſt, and ſet a top of the world and the things of the world with you; my friend of God read me near you in the life of God, but, Oh! it would be ſad to me to feel
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47206:23"/>any of you, with whom I have had Union in the Lord by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to be degenerated and drawn aſide by the love of this preſent World, and the wiles of the Enemies: which will be preſented in this time of tryal by perſwading to ſtay at home or reſt a while until the heat of proſecution be over, as it hath done ſome already in ſome places, which when they appear in the face of the truth it will be their ſhame, becauſe they have harkned to the deceipt of their hearts, and not unto the truth as it is in Jeſus; which never makes aſhamed but bears the Croſs and diſpiſes the ſhame and runs the tace with patience becauſe of the joy that is ſet before them. So my beloved Brethren and Siſters, let nothing perſwade you to fly the Croſs at any time leſt you ſhould loſe your Crown of courage and boldneſs, and ſo be covered with ſhame and contempt, neither let any that do fly the Croſs at any time be your example; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw them into the fellowſhip and love of the croſs again, by your example of faithfulneſs and obedience, and by your not giving heed to ſeducing Spirits, but perſevering on in the Goſpel of the Kingdom of Patience; bearing them as Children who be weak and tender among you. But that which is hard and would not obey the Goſpel is for the hammer, and for the Sword of Gods Spirit, that it may be broken down, and all made as a plain before him; and ſerve him in true feer with a perfect love and upright heart, out of all forms, ſhews or forms of Godlineſs; in the true power and ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the pure holy life, which he hath raiſed up in us, to bear his heavenly Image under his heavenly banner, which is love: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we are to make wair in much patience in this day of Battle, wherein they are fighting againſt us with a cauſe, and we cannot reſiſt them, with Sword nor with Spear, but in patience ſuffer under them all during the Lords time, in which I reſt and bid you all farewell,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>This was as a part of my dear love to you my Friends, becauſe I wiſh you well, William Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47206:23"/>
            <p>DEar friends that ſuffer in <hi>Carlile</hi> Priſon for <hi>non</hi> payment of Tyths, or otherwiſe in bearing a pure Teſtimony for the Holy God of eternal life unto you is my dear love, and the tender Salutation of my life, ye ſufferers for the Lord, do it with thearfulneſs of heart, in the tenderneſs of your Spirits, towards the only true God and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> whom he hath ſent a light into the world, to lighten the blind Eyes, and be the Glory of his People, in the midſt of Tribulations, Perſecutions or ſufferings, and friends I know that you are not unſenſible of the eternal love of God which is more in this day, then the whole world, bleſſed be his holy name for ever, friends its no marvel that you ſuffer perſecution for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake, ſeing the hard heartedneſs &amp; cruelty that is in the world through unbelief and hardneſs of heart, amongſt the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men, who in theſe days have ſet themſelves againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed, his People and choſen ones, whom God hath gathered, and not men, therefore friends of the ſame flock &amp;c ſheep of his foald, be you gathered together in the Lord, and feel his daily love over all, and above all your Perſecuters and heads of your Enemies, in the daly Croſs and power of the righteous God of Heaven and Earth who gives you dominion over all in his power and authority to ſtand in the day of Tryal during the Lords time (unto the time of God over all; who is to be waited on above all, bleſſed for ever, who hath called you and us for that very purpoſe, that we may waite upon his name, and feel his ſtrength and bleſſed preſence and loving power, in which, friends you may have boldneſs with good Courage to teſtifie of his name, unto all the world in your ſufferings, and in your Converſation, as the Lord makes way in your heart for the glory of his truth and the honour of his eternal name, which is become great amongſt us, and is the ſtrong Tower of the righteous, and ſafe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place of his people in the Storms and in the Tempeſt, he his the ſure ſtay of all them that truſts in him and ſtands to him in all Tryals and trouble whatſoever: The Lord kindles up his own Spirit in them and riaſes up his own Seed, which he hath bleſſed, to magnifie his mercys over all, and Rejoyce in the hearts of his called ones, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ones, to place his name among in this day of his living truth, in which he is much made manifeſt by the vallour of his Power which raigns in his Saints and faithful Servants, to the glory of his name, and counts the preſent ſufferings of this life nothing, to the glory that ſhall be revealed, oh the endleſs love of God that is manifeſted in our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47206:24"/>hearts, is it paſt expreſſing with my tongue, or relating with my pen, but this is my pure ſatisfaction, that you know the Lord, and is ſenſible men of his eternal truth, which is able to fill your hearts with praiſes unto God, and rejoyce in the midſt of trouble, and make you willing to lay down your lives for his ſake, if he ſhould require it, for his Teſtimony is true you know, and can ſeal to it, in your ſufferings with the reſt of many more of your Brethren and Siſters, fellow Sufferers in this day who Witneſſes their lives raiſed through, ſufferings, who rejoyces that they are found worthy, not being weary nor thinking time long, but waits with much patience the Lords time, &amp; ſome of our friends is releaſed already in laying down their bodys in this their preſent ſufferings for the Lord, which they did I believe in much joy of heart, a lightſomneſs of mind, to the preaching of the truth of God, and incouragment of friends in the truth, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces with the faithful over all to the praiſe and glory of his name for ever, and friends here is Copies of two Papers that were ſet upon their Corpſes, as they were had to then burial places, and after ſpread abroad in the Country, and ſent up and down amongſt friends, and you may ſend Copies of them, and you may ſee Service for them amongſt friends or others, if it be into <hi>Northumberland</hi> or in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as you ſee way made there, may beſervice in ſending them abroad, ſo I reſt your dear friend in the eternal truth of God and a ſufferer for the ſame becauſe I cannot ſwear.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Willam Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>TO all you who ſay your are the Seed of <hi>Abraham, Abraham</hi> believed God and ſo was found Righteous, and all you that ſay you are of the ſame Seed, and not in the ſame belief, I ſay you are not the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> did not the God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> promiſe by <hi>Moſes,</hi> (whom you ſay you believe) that he would raiſe up a Prophet, like unto him, and him the people ſhould hear in all things, and they that would not here that Prophet, ſhould be cut of from among the People, ſo to you who are called Jews was I moved to write theſe few lines, and to exhort you to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet whom God promiſed to raiſe, and I witneſs him raiſed, and the goverment is laid on him; and of his dominion there ſhall be no end, and ſo to him I exort you all, he is near to you even in your hearts and in your Conſciences teaching you to deny all that is contrary to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did not <hi>Moſes</hi> ſay that the word is nigh thee in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47206:24"/>thy heart and in thy mouth to do it, People this word become fleſh and dwelt among us, and this fleſh was Crucified but the word lives and abides forever, in which the Lord is worſhipped and all other worſhips is Abomnable unto him, doth he not ſay he is weary with the Sacrifices, yea truely people he is wearyed with them, for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is in his Elected one, doth not the God of <hi>Iſreal</hi> ſay behold my Servant whom I uphold, my Elect in whom my Soul delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I put my Spirit upon him, and he ſhall bring forth Judgment to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> verily people he is Judging the ſecrets of all hearts both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſo again I exhort you all to turn your minds to within, and ſee if the light will not judge righteouſly for the God of <hi>Iſreal,</hi> and will ſhew you plainly that he was a true Prophet whom your Fathers believed not, and to this Prophet muſt you come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you know the God of <hi>Iſreal</hi> even this word which is nigh in your mouth and in your hearts, ſo none of you be aſhamed to ſtoop, to this word which is nigh, did not the God of <hi>Iſreal</hi> ſay that though the Children of <hi>Iſreal</hi> were as the Sand of the Sea, yet a remnant was to be ſaved ſo ſee which of you is of that remnant and what you are ſaved from, for they who are ſaved are ſaved from ſin and made clean by this word of Life, but them who lives in ſin and uncleaneſs, are neither Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> no Servants to the God of <hi>Iſreal,</hi> but are a diſhonour to the God of <hi>Iſreal,</hi> as alſo many are who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt in words, and lives not in the life of Chriſt, ſuch are a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to his name and his woe, is upon them, but do not you ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at them, for their deſtruction is of themſelves, for though they be proud or lyers, or coveteous, they have not ſo learned of him, for no ſuch thing was found in him but the Light in you judges and condemns theſe things in both them and you, and ſo to this we exhort you all which teaches truth in the inward parts and this is it the Lord requires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>We deſire you <hi>Engliſh</hi> men to read this Paper.</head>
            <p>ALL people repent and turn to the Lord God the Creator of all things in whoſe power we ſtand witneſſes againſt all manner of evil, as it doth appear, and reproveth it as we are moved of the Lord and for this cauſe are we hated of the world, but we marvel not, for it hated him even <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> who is the Light of the world which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47206:25"/>this Light is in you all, reproving you for ſin, and every evil work, and all that is willing to be guided by it, it leadeth out of the vanities of the world, and not to Faſhion our ſelves like unto this world, and herein do we become a prey to the wicked and a gazing ſtock to the Nations in this day of the Lord, but we have found him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that promiſes in obediance to him we ſhall eat the good of the Land, and now we know him made manifeſt in the fleſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying he works of the Devil, and giving victory over the world and the Luſts thereof, and truly people this is in love to all your Souls to whom it may come to be read, and to this turn your minds, that would redeem your Souls out of death, the Light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> which Comprehendeth all them that live in wickedneſs be they never ſo high or low; it ſearcheth the heart and tryeth the reins, and is a ſure witneſs for God, and Condemns all the proud and wanton ones and the high and lofty ones, and will bring them down to the ground, and this hath been revealed by his Son to us, and we are bold to declare is among you, that God may be clear in all his judgments, for he is juſt in all his doings and hath not brought deſtruction upon any without warning them aforehand, ſo prize your time you know not your hour, and make no mock at ſin, nor ſcorn not the Lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, it is of his own good will that he hath revealed theſe things unto babes and ſucklings, and hid them from the Eyes of the wiſe and prudent, and thus do we witneſs in our meaſures and do return him praiſe to whom all praiſe and honour doth belong and he will not give it to any other, and he hath ordayned the fooliſh things of this world to confound the wiſdom of the wiſe and to bring to nought the underſtanding of the prudent, and all that would be wife let them firſt become Fooles that they may grow wiſe, for the wiſdom of God is fool ſhneſs to the world, and mans wiſdom muſt be deſtroyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever he know the wiſdom of God, (for man by wiſdom knows nor God), for what as may be known of God is manifeſt in you, and ſo friends to the Light of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the only Son of God (the Father of life) turn your minds, and with it ſearch your ſelves honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſee how ye ſtand juſtified in the ſight of God, and aproved in his Light, which doth never aprove of any evil but condmns all unrighteouſneſs, in whomſover it doth ariſe, yea the very thoughts and intent of your hearts are ſeen in this Light, and comprehended, ſo all be warned and take heed how ye deſpiſe them who are ſent of the Lord ſinglely and ſimplely to fore-warn you of the evil to come though they be never ſo ſimple; yet faithful to him who hath called, and is willing to waite in his council, not fearing what man doth unto
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47206:25"/>us, but are willing to ſuffer any thing for righteouſneſs ſake knowing that ſufferings was ever the Saints portion, whoſoever killed them thought they did God ſervice, therefore take heed to the Light, and ſee what you do, for we are not aſhamed to bear our Teſtimony for <hi>Jeſus</hi> before any, for it is Truth and that never makes aſhamed, and our lives is not in our own hands, neither dare we fly from the Lords Conucil, to feed the wiſdom of man but to that of God in you all, do we hope to be made manifeſt, though it is croſs to the firſt nature at preſent, yet upon your beds conſider and in the Light examin whether you did ſee us act or ſpeak any thing that was not of the truth, and we deſire to be convinced of it by Scripture otherwiſe be aſhamed to ſpeak againſt us, if you find us not according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nay glory to God, it is for no evil you can hate us, but becauſe we cannot follow to the ſame exceſs of Riot, therefore you ſpeak evil of us; now to that of God in you all let it judge between you and us, whether you do not love a drunkard better then be that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves him, ye or nay, or a ſwearer or lyer, or a conereous, prophane, proud Perſons, or they who are in the Faſhiens of the world which is vain, better then them who are redeemed out of them, and ſtands witneſſes againſt them, yea or nay, all theſe are works of darkneſs which the Children of God have no fellowſhip with but are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, hath the God of this world ſo far blinded your Eyes that you cannot ſee theſe to be the works of the Devil; and is not this a diſhonor to our Nation, that ſuch curſed fruit as pride and haughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, lightneſs and vainneſs as doth appear in many of you ſhould be brought out of it, (to wit our Nation) think it not ſtrange if the Lord ſmite you with a curſe for theſe things, nor count us not deceivers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot ſpeak peace to you for there is no peace to the wicked faith our God, and is it not adiſhenour to our Nation that ſo many of you ſhould be comed out of it, having not the love of God in you may read <hi>Chriſts</hi> own words on <hi>John 5th and</hi> 41, 42, 43, <hi>and</hi> 44. <hi>the verſes.</hi> O bluſh and be aſhamed that you would lay the diſhonour of our Nation upon thoſe who are innocent and harmleſs fearing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God, who hath power over us all, therefore repent and turn to the Lord God of life and Light leaſt ſuddain deſtruction come upon you, and this in love to all your Souls whether you will hear or forbear.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. H. W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:47206:26"/>
            <head>Here follows a Letter written to Captain <hi>Loaler</hi> whin he was in <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> in <hi>Weſtmoreland</hi> with his Soldiers written in the behalf of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnal Walker</hi> and <hi>George Benſon,</hi> who had Well packs to <hi>Kendal</hi> and was ſent into viſit him in Priſen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the Prieſts.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALL you Prieſts and great Scholars who is in your Tongues of humane Learning, and is proud of it, take heed to your ſelves that you ſet not your <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> above the head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Son of God, who is the life and the power of God, and ſo make a God to your ſelves, of your great learning, which is humane and can never give the knowledge of God, for <hi>Pilat</hi> who delivered <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be Crucified of the Jews, cauſed <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> to be ſet over <hi>Chriſts</hi> Head, take head, I ſay unto you, you proud Scholars that you do not ſo, for the Lord is greived with your Pride and Preſumtion of Tongues, which may be cut of in a moment, and when you dye your Tongues dyes with you, but the pure living God endures for ever, ſo you ſend Scholars and fooliſh Prieſts, who is making to your ſelves a God after your own way, and will not have him after his own way, which is Chriſt within manifeſted in the fleſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Devils work now in People; as he did great Miracles in the days of his Fleſh among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve then, no more then ye can believe that he is now made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in ſinful fleſh, deſtroying the Devils work in the fleſh, that all through him might be ſaved from the Devils work, which is ſin and wickedneſs; would you ſeparate God from poor ignorant People, that would believe in the light of his Son in their own hearts, and confine him to your great Schools of Humane Learning, that none can know the way of God but you; alas for you, for all your Tongues of humane Learning, you are no nearer knowing of Chriſt now in this diſpenſation of revealing himſelf in man, then <hi>Pilat</hi> was that delivered him up to the <hi>Jews</hi> in that day and time, and you are worſe then he, for he did it not willful, but would have let him go; So ſee where your <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> is, while you are ignorant of Chriſt the true Light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world; here the poor, blind and ignorant may have the benefit of Chirſt, as they believe in the light that gives the true knowledge of God whom to know is life, and that never dies, and here is none
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47206:26"/>ſhut out of knowing God; I ſay the Lord ſhuts none out, as you would do with your Scholarſhip if you could, but the Lord is riſen, and he did ariſe in the days paſt to confound the wiſdom of the wife, and bring to nought the undrſtanding of the Prudent, he is ſetting up his Son to Raign in the hearts of his People that believes in his name, and they are not aſhamed to confeſs his name before the men of this generation, who ſeems mighty in their day, but the Lord is blaſting the wiſdom of man, and hath ſaid it ſhall not rule over his People, for they have been a pray over long to thir Mouths, that have ſaid the Lord ſaith, when he hath never ſpoken to them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this I ſay unto you fooliſh and not wiſe, who is proud of your <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> and thinks that God cannot be known in any other way then your teaching of him, you are deceived, for God will not be mocked by you, for he is ſetting up his Son to Raign a top of all that ever hath been ſet a top of him, either in this time or in times paſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <head>Here follows ſeveral Letters that were written to thoſe in Authority when he was Priſoner in <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Goal for not Swearing.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Judges of the Aſſiſe at <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>JUdge or Judges I deſire them or you to read this little Note, and then conſider the poor mans ſtate, that ſuffers for the Lord God eternal, and his holy Truth, as it is in Jeſus, and dare not diſobey his Comands manifeſteſt in his heart, that he may do them whereſoever he be, and obey his ſayings, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay,</hi> whatſoever is more than theſe cometh of evil, and the ſame Chriſt commands to do the truth, and to ſpeak the truth from my heart whereſoever I be, in all places and at all times, in the which I deſire that I may be kept faithful to the end, that I may live in peace with my eternal God of Heaven and of Earth, and follow peace with all men, that be upon the face of the whole Earth, for the Lord God hath called me to peace, and out of wars and ſtrife; Although in the year 1648. I was in wars for the King, and did remain with faithfulneſs unto the end, till we were not a Party able to ſtand any longer, and took leave of my Captain, who did bid me ſhift for my ſelf, which was but ſorrowful to me, and that night was I taken Priſoner, and ſtript to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47206:27"/>Shirt from my back, and that Night had like to been ſtarved to death, and afterwards ſed in Priſon with a penny a day, and ſhamefully uſed in Priſon, and had not left to my back, that any would have given me a peny for, and much more then this did I ſuffer for the Kings ſervice, which I might have eſcaped all them, if I would have taken up Arms with the other Party then; and have betrayed my friend, which thing my heart ſtood againſt, and truly friends I muſt relate much concerning my ſufferings, with a heavy heart, becauſe of ſo little regard that was taken of me, and my poor coming home, nor never gave me a penny pay to this day, neverheleſs I freely wiſh that you and all men knew the reality and truth of my heart to the King and all his true Subjects much more might I write but would not be tedious in writing very much; I am a poor man and hath a ſmall Family whoſe mentenance depends only on my labours, by which I did mentain them well, but now I cannot becauſe I am here in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for my Conſcience ſake, becauſe I cannot ſwear but ſtands in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Chriſts Commands, my Allegiance to the King ſtands in Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs and truth, which I hope I ſhall reman into the end, ſo I deſire that I might have free liberty to live at home and Labour for my Family.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Wilſon a poor man and means well.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>One to the Juſtices and Magiſtrates.</head>
               <p>FRiends, Friends that be in Authority a few words from a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of yours, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith Swear not all, this is <hi>Chriſts</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Swear not at all, and they that loves me keeps my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> (marke) and be not offended at any of his Servants which keeps his ſaying, and cannot ſwear at all, but lets their comuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation be yea, yea, nay, nay, for what as is more cometh of evil as ſaith <hi>Chriſt, Matt.</hi> 5. Truely friends my heart is turned towards God with many more of my brethern in this the day of our God, and we cannot Swear at all for we have learned obediance unto his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin and therefore we are willing to keep his ſayings, whatever we ſuffer by man for friends conſider I ſhall put my caſe with the reſt of my brethrens who be of the ſame Faith, to your own ſelves to judge: <hi>Chriſt</hi> he ſaith Swear not at all, &amp; you ſay you muſt Swear, ſo whether it be better to obey God or man Judge ye, likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith to his brethren above all things my breathren Swear not at all leaſt you ſall into Condemnation <hi>Jam.</hi> 5, but you ſay Swear
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47206:27"/>or elſe you ſhall go to Priſon, conſider this friends and Judge Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, whether is to be obeyed now if ſufferings muſt be, we theſe to ſuffer for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayings rather then for much ſayings, for if we do not Swear we muſt fall into Priſon, and if we do Swear we are ſure to fall into Condemnation (marke that), but it is better for us to obey God then man man ſo we cannot Swear at all whatever we ſuffer, I hope we ſhall not break our peace with God for pleaſing men, for we know the Lords care is over them that fear him and he will viſit for theſe things; So take heed how you cauſe us to ſuffer, for not ſwearing counting it a breach of your Law, for us to keep <hi>Chriſt</hi> own ſayings, that is offended in any of you to ſee us wear our own hats on our heads, and to here us ſpeak Gods truth plainly from our hearts, without ſwearing, was ever any of Gods people offended at theſe things, or cauſed any to ſuffer for not ſwearing, conſider friends and take heed how you oppreſs tender Conſciences and caſt into Priſon them that cannot Swear for Conſcience ſake, and lets Swearers have their Liberty; for I am one willing to ſuffer for not ſwearing rather then to deny <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe I love and obey the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which ſaith Swear not at all.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>VVilliam VVilſon</hi> Servant of the ſame Lord.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>One to Juſtice <hi>Fleming</hi> of <hi>Rydale.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH Juſtice <hi>Fleming</hi> that ever this report ſhould be ſounded in our Ears, that within thy Libertys ſuch ſpoyling ſhould be amongſt thy Nighbours, we never had the like in our Pariſh, nor never expected that our own Juſtice ſhould have made ſuch work, as ſet men of ſpoyling true mens goods; who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves dare not ſpoyle nor do any hurt to any man upon the face of of the whole Earth, becauſe of their Conſcience towards the God of Heaven, which is appeared in theſe latter days, and is come and hath taken up his aboad with them and keeps them unto himſelf, out of all ſpoyling again when they are ſpoyled of their Cloaths &amp; of Horſes and their goods which they had honeſtly gotten by their hard labour and induſtry and hath learned to live peaceably amongſt their Neighbours, and a godly life in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> who ſaith learn of me; but not to ſpoyle true mens goods, who for Conſcience ſake cannot Swear nor break of their, godly Meetings which God hath ſet up and not man; therefore conſider and call in the ſpoylers from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47206:28"/>ſpoyling of true men thy Neighbours, who have none in the Earth to plead their cauſe but gives themſelves up to God, and all they have to ſuffer for his ſake, having received the earneſt of the Spirit, and the aſſurance of etern I life from which they never intend to fly, for all that ever mortal man can do unto them in this caſe, for it is in matter of holy worſhip to our God which all the ſpoylers in the world is out of, and all ungodly men an truths gainſayers which be in theſe latter days and though many Fools and Bablers that is applauded in theſe latter days for their fooliry <hi>and their fordneſs Jaging and wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the ſtreats like fools in a play, the Lord hates ſuch who fears not him that hath made them, but walks in wickedneſs making a mock at ſin, and ſporting themſelves againſt the Lord and them that fear his name; of which ſort I am one and am not aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his name among men though it be to my great loſs, and hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in this world, as all my neighbours can tell and my wife and little children knows the want of me, as thine may do of thee in time for ought I know, which I do not deſire more then I deſire my own ſhould want me, but if thou knew what it were I believe thou would not be ſo hard hearted and my friend Willam <hi>Grave</hi> is lying at the point of Death and this day one Prioner is lying dead and its a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and a mercy of God I am not ſo to, and many more of us you have caſten into Priſon, and not one of you that comes to viſit us, but we may rather think you wiſh us all dead, as thy brother <hi>Willam</hi> did babling below a man and much more a Captain, and thy Cozen <hi>Will. Kirby</hi> reported the night you had done that wicked act of caſting us all into Priſon, that you had, had an honourable Bench, and that thou was ſuch a man as was not in many parts (and your whole ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice had almoſt been taken up about the Quakers) and you had hall'd the Fox and ſtayed his <hi>Hambrough</hi> Quaker from traveling, or the like words to that purpoſe, which is below a man or man-hood to vant of Caſting men into Priſon, it irkes my heart that ever men ſhould be ſo Fooliſh, as to do as you have done with us, in ſending us as thou ſent us, and its thought cauſed the death of two and the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of others, it make the Country cry out ſhame, ſhame, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it vexes me that my Country man ſhould looſe his honor in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, hard againſt poor Quakers as many calls us and had gained it ſo in other things, as I have heard thy name honoured among men where I have been both for carrage and underſtanding ſo Juſtice <hi>Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> conſider and let men of tender Conſciences have their liberty as others doth in other places, and be not ſo hard of the Lords people Even who are engaiged to meet together fearing the Lord, as ſaith
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47206:28"/>the Scriptures they that ſeared the Lord met often together and ſpake often one unto another, and the Lord harkered and heard, it and a book of rememberance was written for them that feared the Lord, and thought upon his name, as we are Witneſſes of is thoſe days, (though we be hated of men not knowing the Scriptures) and as we have believed <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Scriptures ſo do we keep his commands, who ſaith he that loves me keeps my ſayings, who ſaith Swear not at all, and in obediance to this very thing we ſtand, who ſuffers here in <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Caſtle becauſe we cannot Swear nor break the Commands of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> which if we ſhould it were a ſhame to us, and below our honour and Scollarſhip which we have learned in <hi>Chriſt</hi> that never Swear, and ſo taught his <hi>Diſciple</hi> who ſufferred for his Doctrin in their days, as we do more in our days, with much Joy of heart that we are counted worthy to ſuffer for his ſake and bear our Teſtimony to all the world, that God is true and every man a lyer who doth not truth, and ſo remaines in his ſins which truth ſets free from, and ſo we trample upon thoſe things which is below; if we bear our Teſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony unto death, as ſome of our friends and brethren have already done in theſe naſty holes and ſtinking Priſons, where men may eaſily get their death; I could gladly find to be with thee that we might reaſon together upon the things of which ſo greatly doth concern our everlaſting peace and honour in the Lord, which is far above all the honour in this world in my Eye, it is above the hat and knee, which men may throw in the mire and where lyes it then; but that honour which is from above is placed in the heart, and is there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for ever; and if it were about other things as matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kings ſervice I could relate unto thee my ſufferings to be great, as to me, and none of you took care for me then: I might then do as I could for you; and I have ſufferred ſince in <hi>Clivers</hi> days for that ſervice, and I was in Priſon for my Conſcience ſake at <hi>Carlile</hi> and that unjuſtly too, what is it I am born to do to ſuffer ſtill and that unjuſtly too both then for the King, and now by his friends and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had as much as a penny pay to this day, cannot that I believe was was Caſten and gathered in their days for me, as <hi>Edward Benſon</hi> of <hi>Hycloſe</hi> &amp; <hi>John Midlefel</hi> of <hi>Langdale</hi> knew them: but the times turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo their minds turned, and kept what they had for ought I know, and little regarded my Impriſonment and poor coming home which made me think it of my ſelf, being ſo poor; and knew not how to mend it when others mockt at me and I might have gotten away as they did which ſhewed their Lovalty to the King to be but ſmall, when mine was made manifeſt, ſo I think it were little enough if I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47206:29"/>had my pay now to help mee in Priſon, and I hope pity will now in thy heart towards towards my Wife and little Children, that they may not want or elſe what Charity lives with thee, ſo its for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that I ſuffer here, which I love to reaſon for with Miniſters or Magiſtrates or any men that fears God of Heaven, and loves the Serip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which is uſeful to deſid. Controverſies about Religion, and this is the thing that is ſettled in my heart, and my deſire is that I may labour in the fear of the Lord and not be chargable to any man, and live a Godly life, and lay open wickedneſs and deceipt to the view of the whole world, as the eternal God move it in my heart, unto whom I ſtand in obediance, and dare not ſwear at all; Thy friend and Neighbour <hi>Willam Wilſon</hi> and a lover of thy ſouls and everlaſting peace, and if I could Swear I ſhould take that Oath as ſoon as any that you ſet much by.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Caſtle <date>the <hi>9th of the 12th</hi> Month, 1663.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to <hi>Edward Stanley</hi> of <hi>Dalegarth</hi> in <hi>Eſhdale.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EDward Stanley</hi> I deſire the read this paper over to the end with patience if thou canſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>E. S.</hi> thy ungodly deeds ſhews thee forth to be an ill ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample amongſt thy Neighbours, and they that fears not God learns at thee, and loves thy evil deed, and thy ungodly ways is a ſtrength to to thoſe that fears not God, but with thy ſelf would not have God nor good men to live among you, but ſtrives with ſtrength and cruelty to ſhut the Contry of them, that fears the Lord and worſhips his moſt holy name, which ungodly men and curſed Swearers is not fit to name, the Lord remembers all thy doings that thou haſt done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people that fears his name and he will not forgit thy cruel doings that thou did unto <hi>John Gunſon</hi> his wife and little Children and <hi>James Stanton</hi> and his Innocent life in which he lives unto God and dareſt not be offenced in <hi>Chriſt</hi> for all the world, if thy weight had been ten times greater then that thou haſt already laid on him, he hath ſo truly learned Chriſt; Oh the Lowing of <hi>John Gunſons</hi> Beaſts when he cauſed their Ears to be cut off, ſhall riſe up in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt thee, and the harmleſs Sheep thou took from <hi>James Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> ſhall plead his innocent cauſe and condemn the to thy face, and every Fleece of Wool thou took from him, ſhall cry out againſt thee, and all their goods thou ſo evilly got ſhall do thee nor thine no good,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47206:29"/>and they ſhall live and praiſe the Lord, when thou ſhall fear and ſhame to hear of thy ungodly deeds, the very name of God ſhall fear thy Soul, and good men thou ſhall ſhun, and Hills and Mountains ſhall thee fly; O whether wilt thou run, we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to Worſhip God, his Truth will bear us out, it is no other thing we ſuffer for, and therefore we are ſtout, and doth not fear the loſs of all that ever we poſſeſs, the Lord will plead our harmleſs cauſe, and will deliver us;</p>
               <l>And all our Foes will ſcattered be as duſt upon a Hill,</l>
               <l>When he will gather his Lambs that doth his holy will;</l>
               <l>Remember how thou went about to do his People wrong,</l>
               <l>VVho in his fear together met, though not contemning long,</l>
               <l>The Lord conſidered well their cauſe, and knew the need they had,</l>
               <l>And brought them home again in time, which made the needful glad,</l>
               <l>And therefore we are not to fear the worſt that man can do,</l>
               <l>For ſerving of ſo good a God that will conſider ſo:</l>
               <l>I have believed the God of heaven that maketh all mankind,</l>
               <l>And do not fear to worſhip him who ever be left behind;</l>
               <l>Conſider well the Poor mans ſtate, that liveth near to thee,</l>
               <l>And do him good if that thou canſt it will thy comfort be,</l>
               <l>For he would do to thee no harm, I fully do believe,</l>
               <l>Nor wrong the things belongs to thee, whatever one would him give,</l>
               <l>Or ſay to him in ſuch caſe, the Lord hath taught him ſo,</l>
               <l>To Pray for him that Perſecutes, and pardon every Foe.</l>
               <p>The Poor mans name is <hi>Nicholas Tyſon,</hi> I belive thou haſt nothing againſt him but for his worſhip to God, and God is without reſpect of perſons, for whoſoever feareth him and works righteouſneſs, is accepted of him, and he will remember all thoſe things that is done againſt thoſe harmleſs people, and will clear their cauſe, and their oppreſſors ſhall not go free; for they are written where they can never be blotted out by the power and cunning ſleights of men; and it grieves many good mens hearts, that ever ſuch unreaſonable men ſhould bear the name of Chriſtians, that work ſuch wicked works for ungodly gain, and uſe the Kings name for a cover: wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly didſt thou work, and evil will be the end of it, if thou look not to it in time, the Lords decree is gone out againſt injuſtice and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deeds that's done againſt his People, that he hath promiſed to preſerve, and deliver out of all their troubles, though they ſuffer for the tryal of their Faith, therefore Repent for thou muſt come to Judgment and an account muſt thou give, and how canſt thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Lord in thoſe things, that makes thee ſhame before
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47206:30"/>men, the world crys out of thee and ſaith it will never be forgotten, it deſerves to be poſted up in the Markets and Steplehouſes, when ſeven years is come and gone, the Lord abhors thy doings, it ſtinks in his Noſtrils, but the poor innocent ſufferers is a ſweet ſmell in his ſight, this is in love to thy Soul, that thou mayſt remember thy evil deeds done and paſt, that thou mayſt learn Repentance in due time, before it be too late, for the Lord wills not the death of a Sinner, but rather that he would turn from his wickedneſs and live; Thy friend and lover of thy Soul, <hi>Willam Wilſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Written in the 9th Month</hi> 1664. <hi>with my own hand.</hi>
                  </date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Letter to</hi> John Ambroſe <hi>Prieſt of</hi> Gaiſſiner in the <hi>County of</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moreland.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JO. Ambroſe</hi> wilt thou remember thy Priſoner, that thou haſt in Priſon for the Lords cauſe, and not for any due debt I owe thee, for if thou wert a Miniſter of Chriſt thou would ask me none, and as thou art not a Miniſter of Chriſt I owe thee none, therefore let me forth of Priſon, that I may go at liberty and do my ſervice, as its required at my hand, or elſe let it fall on thy own neck, and then it will be to heavy for the to bear, yea, and all that will take thy part. This I write unto thee, that I may let thee know that thou haſt the Lords Servant in thy hand, (and will not let me go,) for not paying thee Wages that doth me no ſervice nor work, but the firſt work thou doth to me is ſending me to Priſon, a work we never read of in all the Scriptures, that all the men of God that ever we read on did caſt men into Priſon for their Bellys, but if thou wilt not let me out do as thou will, and let the Lord do as he will, for I am well content; but I muſt remember thee of the evil work which thou has done, in caſting me into Priſon from my Wife and Childred, but the Lord will Plead my cauſe and ſet me at liberty; when thou and all unrighteouſneſs ſhall be made faſt for ever, therefore remember what I have told thee, and do good while thou may, for thy time will ſpend and thy Repentance prove too late, let me not lye here while thou is feeding and feaſting thy ſelf, but remember the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Fatherleſs, as it were Fatherleſs Children thou haſt made by caſting me into Priſon from them, and will not let them have their right the Lord allows them, this muſt ſtand upon thy head thou unrighteous man, if thou wilt not let me go as the Lord
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47206:30"/>requires it of thee, for he hath more for me to do then thou knows on, therefore ſay not but thou art warned from the Lord before thy evil day come upon thee, which will overtake thee as a Theif in the Night, and come upon thee as an armed man, when there is none to deliver thee; ſo ſend thy Letter to fetch me forth if thou will, if thou wilt not, do even as thou will, So I leave thee,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Wilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>
                  <hi>JO. Amborſe</hi> I am here in Priſon upon thy account for about ſix pence or ſeven pence by the year, which I ſhould never have refuſed to pay to thee if I were convinced that thou were one of Chriſts Miniſters, but as I am perſwaded that thou art not, I rather chooſe to ſuffer for the <hi>non</hi> payment of it, then to pay it contrary to that of God in mine own Conſcience; thou had better have taken a Cow or a Horſe form my Wife and Childred, then have caſt me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon from them, the Lord will hear their cry of Oppreſſion, more for want of me, then for the want of either Cow or Horſe, and I would wiſh thee for the good of thy own Soul to let me out again, that I may work for my Living, and it will be more honour to thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, and leſs condemnation before the Lord, if thou have any reſpect either to old or young, Wife or Children, hear their cry for want of me their Father, which if thou will not, I doubt not but the Lord will hear their cry, and deliver when thou canſt not reſiſt, and in the undaunted Spirit of God I can reſt and wait with much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, who am thy friend and lover, though I have a little taſted of thy Envy, yet I deſire the welfare of thy Soul, if poſſible the Lord may grant it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Kendal</hi> 
                     <date>the <hi>29th</hi> of the 9th Month, 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>William VVilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Here follows two ſhort Letters to <hi>John Kirby,</hi> in the behalf of two friends impriſoned by him for Tyths.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JO. Kirby</hi> I can do no leſs then let thee know that we remember theſe two friends of ours, which thou ungodlyly haſt caſt into Priſon for <hi>non</hi> payment of Tyths, and not only we the friends of the Lord, but even the Lord himſelf doth remember them, with many more of his dear Children, who ſuffers for the ſame Holy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, for whoſe ſakes the Lord of Glory will plead with their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47206:31"/>Adverſarys by Fire and Sword, the Lord hath ſpoken it by me, and that thou is one of them that the Lord will plead with for the ſakes of his Servants <hi>George Benſon</hi> and <hi>Richard VValker,</hi> their wives and little Children who is dayly mourning for the loſs of their natural fathers, whom the Lord of life and Glory is as Subject to hear as they are to mourn, and haſt ſaid; Ah, ah, I will eaſe me of mine Adverſarys I will be avenged of mine oppreſſors, I will be known that I am the Lord notwithſtanding my Enemies who promiſe themſelves eaſe and peace when they have done the Devils work by caſting into Priſon, as it is ſaid the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, but the Lord remembers theſe things and will not forget his Servants whom he hath choſen to place his name among, who ſtands faithful unto him them will he deliver one way or other, we need not look how the Lord knows what way makes moſt for his Glory, as I remember the death of <hi>Oliver Atherton</hi> that ſweet Martyr for the Lord in bearing the ſame Teſtimony who the ſame night before he dyed, ſang praiſes to the Lord in a moſt heavenly manner as many Witneſſes can teſtifie, becauſe he ſuffered this lingering Marterdom for the Lord of Glory who ended the tenth, and redeemed him out of the ninth, as it is written in the declaration of his death that was ſet upon his Corps, as he was carryed home to his family to be buryed, as the Counteſs of <hi>Darby</hi> could witneſs who was his great Averſary and Proſecuter into Priſon, who dyed her ſelf about ſix weeks after and then all the reſt were releaſed as by the providence of the Lord whom they ſuffered for: And then they who we made as Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and fatherleſs, for a time were eaſed of their ſufferings, as theſe who are now as poor Widows &amp; fatherleſs Children may die in due Seaſon (as the Lord ſees good) whom thou haſt made through thy Jewiſh cuſtom of taking tenths, though in that day it was lawful for the Jews yet I never read in Scriptures that they ſued at Law for them as thou doeſt, nor received them for that end as thou doeſt, nor made Widdows nor fatherleſs Children as thou doſt nor lay'd men in Priſon for them as thou doth; nor when one Law would not ſerve went to another as thou haſt done, nor never gave Goalers ſtrict charge over them as ſome of you have done, but the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge for theſe things, to whom we leave it for I will repay it ſaith the Lord and this was <hi>I</hi> moved to write by the God of my life unto thee or whom it may concern in the behalf of my brethren and their wives and little Children, who cannot do as much for themſelves, that thou may conſider their caſes, who ſuffers for the Lord and dare not pay Tyths for pleaſing man, and thereby offend God, who hath
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47206:31"/>brought them to make a good Confeſſion of his name before men, and is not aſhamed of their Chriſtian duty to God, who hath redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them out of the ninths, and left them Witneſſes againſt the tenths for his names ſake, Glory to the Lord for ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>VV. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A ſhort Letter to the Prieſts and their hearers.</head>
               <p>FRiends <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> who ſaid he is the way of truth and the life, <hi>John</hi> 1. ſaith alſo, he is Light of the world and whoſoever believes in him ſhall not abide in darkeneſs but ſhall have the Light of life, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. So truely friends this is the Light of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> which ſheweth you ſin, and what is evil in you, and this is that which is not of the world neither can the world receive it; for the whole world lyeth in wickedneſs, but this of God to which we ſpeak doth never conſent unto wickedneſs, but reproveth all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil whatſoever, and ſheweth you that you ſhould not wrong one another but do to all men as ye would they ſhould do to you, friends this is the way of truth, and to ſpeak the truth one to another, this will ſtand in the Light, which is the truth, and truly if you love God you will love the Light, for God is Light, and of Purer Eyes then to behold iniquity, and a meaſure of the Spirit is given to every one of you by manifeſtation, to profit withall ſo every one ſearch honeſtly your own hearts, and ſee how you have profited with it, for truly an acount muſt you give of your deeds done (in) your bodies whether they be good or evil; now all evil is manifeſt to be of the Devil as lying, ſwearing, theft, drunkenneſs, deſembling, deceiving, with the reſt of all ungodly actions, therefore repent and forſake your ſins and return from the evil of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for the Lord wills not the death of a ſinner, but rather that you would return from your wickedneſs and live to ſerve him alone in that which is holy and juſt and good, for to live in ſin, and luſts of uncleaneſs, is death and deſtruction, and dear people ſtrive to enter in at the ſtaite gate which leadeth to life, and few there be that find it, but wide is the way and broad is the gate that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that find it; ſo <hi>I</hi> dearly exhort you all to read your conditions honeſtly and ſee how you ſtand juſtified in the Light, of the Son of God, and your time all to prize and turn to the Light, while you have the Light reproving you for ſin in Secret when as no mortal Eye doth behold, and by believing and obeying it: it will lead you out of darkneſs and this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47206:32"/>is the true Teacher and near unto every one of you all and cannot be removed into a corner but is preſent with us and you at all times, and in all places, and ſees the very thoughts and intents of the heart, and no other way is to the Father but by the Son who is the true Light that lighteth every man that comes into the world and this is in love to all your Souls, let him that readeth underſtand, and you that teacheth others, whether you are taught your ſelves of him, who is the true teacher <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Secondly, and whether they that are taught of him, are taught to ſettle themſelves at one certain place for ſo much a year, as can agreed betwixt partys. Thirdly, whether they that be ſo are not of that ſort that <hi>Eſaiah</hi> ſaith, ſeeks their gain from their Quarter, and the hireling that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith flyeth. Fourthly, whether they be not of that ſort that ſtands praying in the Sinagogue, hath upermoſt places in the Aſſemblys, and is called of men Maſter. Fifthly, whether they have not mens Perſons in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration becauſe of advantage, and reverenceth, honour one of anothor and calleth men Maſters. Sixly, whether theſe be not of the ſame gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that <hi>Jermiah</hi> ſaith, ſteal the words from their neightbour. and ſaith, the Lord ſaith, when the Lord hath not ſpoken to them Sevenly, whether theſe be not in the way of <hi>Canan,</hi> envy and <hi>Balaum</hi> ſeeing after gifts and rewards.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Scotland</hi> to friends about <hi>Kendal</hi> in <hi>Weſtmoreland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEAR friends in and about <hi>Kendal</hi> theſe may ſignifie to you all who is deſirous to heare of me that I am well bleſſed be the Lord for the ſame, and my heart affcted with the deaar love of God unto you my true friends, with whom I have fellowſhip in the heavenly Union and Comfortable Spirit of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal God, who is preſent with us at all times and places, who cannot be ſeperated from his own, from his own life in his people, who hath choſen him for their way, and for their life, &amp; cannot live without him who is life, the Lord of hoſts is his name; he is my life &amp; my daily food, my Soul ſatisfier, &amp; the refreſher of my bowels and inward part, where the world knows me not, and therefore they Judge me like unto themſelves: But my friends with you whom God hath called and choſen, to place his name among is my bleſſed fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the Light of his heavenly Son <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> who hath made
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47206:32"/>choice of us without reſpect of Perſons; O my dear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> may all be continued in faithfulneſs and rightneſs of heart, unto him in fear, to walk while we have one day to ſpend; my friends feal Gods to love you as at the firſt, and yours to him as at the begining and ſo ſhall the truth never become as an old thing nor you in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure dye to it, my dear friends its far from me to ſtand up to teach or inſtruct any of you but as the Lord hath freely made me pertaker and ſharer with you of his devine heavenly love, I cannot but in the remembrance of the ſame return you an anſwer of the continuance of his love to my Soul, that you thereby may be remembred of the ſame, that we may feel one another in the everlaſting love that can never decay, nor never be forgetten by them that loves God and the bleſſed and pure appearance of his Son <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Light of the world, my friends ſince I parted with you I have been in the furtheſt part of all <hi>Scotland,</hi> as to the <hi>Maineland,</hi> and have had good ſervice there for the Lord, for people, was very willing to heare the truth and enclined in words very much, but you know the old agents that was ever ready to ſtir up help and Inſtruments againſt the true Light the now ſhines (to wit the Prieſts) of this generation but all will fail them, its God muſt be Gloryfied, the Prieſts worſhip will come to an end, they have had worſhip enough, its God muſt now be worſhiped, he will not give his Glory to another, and likewiſe in the Iſle of <hi>Stormie</hi> where a dore was open for us, and our Teſtimony received with much gladneſs, and we kindly entertained for a little ſpace while we had freedom; and ſo returned and leaves the work to God; and we were alſo in the Iſles of <hi>Ortners</hi> in the Town of <hi>Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> where there is a very like people in the Lords time but Biſhops and Prieſts have Lordly power over poor people, and keeps them much in Bondage, but they have a very great ſight into the ways of all ſorts of profeſſions, and the true Light diſcovers them all: And ſo my dear friends who have made full proof of the Light of the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in you own hearts: you it is that can give a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſame for while man be not come into full obediance of the Light, he never knows the true ground nor benefit of the ſame, and ſo with my dear love to you all as if I named you all I take leave and reſts your friend in the Lord according to my meaſure.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William VVilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:47206:33"/>
               <p>FRiends I could well have found to have written to you ear this but being ſo far diſtant, I could not ſee how it could be ſafely conveyed, neither was I very free till I ſaw ſomething of my return, which is now prety large for we are at this preſent, come within about fourteen or fifteen miles of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> and ſo as God permits after viſiting friends in my way I hope to the Lord to ſee you with comfort ere long; be ſure to let my wife and friends of <hi>Haukſhead</hi> Meeting here from you, or elſe ſend them theſe lines on a Second day with my love to them all.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Auworthy</hi> 
                     <date>the fifth day of the ſeventh Month, 1673.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>William Wilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>YOU that uſurp Authority over poor people, and bears rule by your means, the day of the Lord haſten upon you which will ſtrip you naked and bare, and reward you according to your works, and then where will your Authority be you Rulers and Magiſtrates who Rules not according to the juſt Law of God, but according to your own wills, the Lord will juſtly recompence his wrath and vengence upon your unrighteouſneſs, you corupt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and fruitleſs trees which plead for ſin and imperfection, and here you uphold the Devils Kingdom who raigns in ſin, and here you are found Enemies to God and his righteouſneſs, and I am a witneſs for the living God, againſt you all who acts contrary to the juſt Law of God, and bears Teſtimony to his name, who is the Author and finiſher of my faith, and perfects his own work and clenſeth from all ſin by his blood, all that walk in the Light, as he is in the Light; but you who walk in darkneſs hath not this hope neither that faith which purifies the heart, but are going on in the broad way, profeſſing God and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with your mouth, Proſecutes the life and power, as did the ſame generation in all ages paſt; halling, beating, ſcoffing, ſcorning, and ſhuting into Priſon them that did confeſs his name, and declared againſt all deceipt operly, againſt all ſin and evil as they were moved, but the Lord will be avenged for theſe things therefore haſt to Repentance and amend your lives, for the Kingdom of God is at hand.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Wilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:47206:33"/>
               <p>ALL people that deſires to ſerve the living God in newneſs of life muſt of neceſſity turn your minds into the Light of his Son <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in your own hearts, for that is he that gives the true knowledge of God whom to know is life eternal, and this is he whom God hath ſent into the world to be a Light to lighten all people, that through him they might believe and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for he is the Saviour of his people from their ſins, ſo people what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever makes manifeſt ſin is Light and whatſoever is reprovable is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd with the light, for the light proves the world of ſin, of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of judgment, and this is he that ſets up true Judgment in the heart and gives, thee to deſcern between the good and the evil, and lets the ſee the thoughts of thy heart in which thou doſt behold thy State how thou ſtands approved unto God, and this is near thee &amp; will never deceive thee, and as thou finds thy obediance unto God, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Light of his Son, which never conſents to the evil of thy doings, ſo ſhalt thou find Gods power and Spirit beating witneſs, with thy Spirit, that thou art a Son of God guided by the Spirit of God, and cannot fulfil the luſts of the Fleſh and this muſt every one come to witneſs, whoever comes to witneſs the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to be their Saviour, who is the Saviour of his people from their ſins, for while man and woman lives in their ſin they are dead while they leive, and all dutys, performances and prayers, to and profeſſions of God and Chriſt is no more then if they cut off a dogs neck or offered up Swins blood, for the works of man are a vaine thing, while he knows not the works of the Devil deſtroyed in him: that he may know God to work all his works in him, and through him, to his own praiſe and Glory for ever: and the heart of man, can never be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right unto God, while in the old nature with old <hi>Adam</hi> in the fall which brought death upon all men; and in that ſtate man cannot ſtand up for the Lord as a living witneſs againſt ſin, and wickedneſs, and all unrighteouſneſs of men, becauſe he remains in death: for all his duties and performances in that nature, is without God and without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the world, and man in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God ſo people as I have ſaid, you that loves and deſires to ſerve the true and living God muſt come to the Light of his Son in your hearts, and be willing to be taught of him, who tells you plainly you ſhould not lye, nor ſwear an oath, nor do to any but as you your ſelves would be done by, and heare you may know a learning of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the good
<pb facs="tcp:47206:34"/>Teacher and Biſhop of your Souls, and this is in love to you all who deſires ſingly after God, for none elſe can receive it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>given forth in <hi>Scotland</hi>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>by <hi>R. R. </hi> and, VVilliam VVilſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter ſent to Juſtice <hi>Willam Kirby</hi> from <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Gaol, <hi>1663.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIllam Kirby</hi> the whole cauſe of my being impriſoned is laid upon thee, for thy Cozen <hi>Fleming</hi> ſaid it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was informed that I was as a traveller, which I heard thee ſay with my own Eares and made anſwer in the open Seſſions, and if this be the cauſe as I am informed, its ſhamful that I ſhould be impriſoned for travelling the Lords buſineſs, ſix or ſeven veirs ſince which was when I ſaw thee in <hi>Hambrough,</hi> it would but be a ſhame to thee that I ſhould publiſh this abroad concerning thee, that I ſhould be caſt into Priſon for this which was paſt ſix or ſeven years ſince being change of government, ſince and an act of Indulgence, ſince an Act of Grace, if it had been a Tranſgreſſion in thoſe days, thou ought not to puniſh me for it now, I believe no Laws in the Land will bear thee out to do it, for I believe your act is for them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts from their houſe or habitation and meets together to the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying of the Kings Subjects which I ſhould be loath to do, being the Kings friend as was manifeſted in the year forty eight, both by my continuance with the longeſt in his ſervice, here and ſuffering impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment and the loſs of all that I had and more, as I can make it appear by my neighbours after I got home, and there was none of the Kings friends that then took any care of me, then I might have been ſtarved for them then, as I am Priſoner by them now; and I have as good reaſon to have this in my mind now by which I had like to have loſt my life, and loſt all I had for obediance to the King: as thou to have my travel for the Lord into <hi>Hambrough</hi> in thy mind, where my brother and I was uſed like dogs, ſometimes by the dogs nature in many of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, which we found therein, pride and haughtyneſs which the Lord will abaſe and bring to nought when we ſhall be exalted for our abediance unto God, and teſtifying of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal truth which ſhall never dye, and of which we ſhall never be aſhamed when ungodly ſinners and wicked men ſhall be conſounded
<pb facs="tcp:47206:34"/>and brought to naught, therefore conſider if envy have reſted in thy mind to do we a miſchief ever ſince that time, it is a wicked deed of thee, and thou had need to amend it and ſhortly to; leaſt the Lord ſhould cut thee off before the time &amp; then it would be too late to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this my friend; And I brought a good meſſuage into the City of <hi>Hambrought</hi> and that unto you that did underſtand my Language but you did receive our meſſuage but badly, and entreated the Lords Servants with many dangers, as we dayly found among you in the ſtreets, and in your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, as my body found by your unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable blows, and thruſting by you <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, the like was never received among the Dutch by us, but our God delivered us then as he will do now to our great comfort, and our eternal Peace, in that we were found faithful in his work, &amp; did never ſhrink to any one of you, whom we found out of the way of God, in wildneſs, wickedneſs, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and vanity, luſtfulneſs, pleaſure and pride of life, which things we boldly bare our Teſtimonys againſt in the Faith, Fear and Power of the Eternal God of Heaven and Earth, which did preſerve us; and will preſerve us, as we in his Faith abide, for whoſe Faith and Teſtimony I ſuffer in Priſon now in <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Caſtle, without any juſt cauſe or breach of any Law, that ſhould have expoſed me ſo impriſonment, but only thy Imformation to Juſtice <hi>Fleming</hi> of my traveling, as it is to me related, therefore the cauſe of my writing is, that thou may take care and overſight of my Wife and Children, which thou haſt cauſed to be left deſolate, by ſtaying me in Priſon from them, and when Juſtice <hi>Fleming</hi> was willing that I ſhould have a little Liberty from the Goaler, and would joyn with the in any thing thou did, as his Brother <hi>Roger</hi> wrote unto thee, then thou did write that the Goaler might let me have ſome liberty, but it moſt be upon his own account, for thou would not meddle in the thing which rather cauſed my ſtreightning then otherways; and alſo <hi>Thomas Watters</hi> of <hi>Bootle,</hi> whoſe time might ill be taken up in lying here, his Wife being near down lying, and having little help about her, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle liberty at this time might do him much good, ſo conſider and let not the ery of innocent Children fall upon thy head, leaſt thou come to be dealt with as thou deal'ſt with us, in keeping us them from help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in their time of need, and we fear thou will be but a bad friend to them in need, therefore let one line or two be under thy hand to the Goaler (if thou would have us do good to our Familys) as ſome others have done before thee, and then it may be well accepted of, ſo to that of God I leave thee, which never wrought evil nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will work evil, thy Friend and a Traveller for the Lord and his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47206:35"/>Truth, <hi>Will. Wilſon</hi> a ſufferer alſo for the ſame, its not this ſlip out of thy mind; but it was even a ſhame thou ſhould ſend ſo many of thy hoeſt Neighbours to Priſon, like Vagabonds from Conſtable to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, as not caring for us, but ſent us away to Priſon, where I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it cauſed the death of two of us, and the third was very near the point of death, if he yet recover, and thou would not come to ſee us, till thou came to work wickedneſs againſt us, as many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds can witneſs for us, by Fining of ſome, and partially ſingling me out, and put the Oath to me, which hath not ſworn this many years, nor never ſhall I fully believe in my heart, neither for nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any man, for I have learned Chriſt and am a Chriſtian, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſwear at all, though thou haſt wickedly ſeparated me from my Wife and Children, which I maintained well with my labour, and kept them from charge; ſo now ſee thou to that, and inquire of them how they can live without me and my maintainance, and let thy Warrant be as ſtrong for the relieving of them, in manner as I did, as it was for carrying me to Priſon, and in giving the Gaoler charge over me in the Seſſions for not ſwearing, and ſo break Chriſts commends, which thing is a ſhame to thee, when it will be a honour unto me, likewiſe a poor man of <hi>Bootle</hi> for coming over to <hi>Swarth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> Meeting, thou proffered him the Oath, and cauſed him to ſtay in Priſon from his Wife and Children, which is an ungodly deed of thee and the reſt that did it: So conſider this, and either let us go to live at home, or take care for our Wives and Children, ſeeing thou haſt power to caſt us into Priſon, ſurely thou haſt power to look to our Charge we have leſt behind us, and think not that it is far to look to <hi>Bootle,</hi> for there is need for the man I know,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thy friend <hi>Willam Wilſon</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to <hi>William Wilſon</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Windermer</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmoreland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the weighty conſideration of the ſervice God hath laid on his Servants to make his name known in the Earth, throughout the whole world, and to declare his love and kindneſs unto the Sons and Daughters of men who are in the fallen State and doth not know the work of God in the new Creation Regeneration and Reſtoration whereby man is reſtored up to God again, out of the fallen State in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47206:35"/>which all men have had a place, and being from God in the fall, and without God in ſin and iniquity which hath made the great ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and being at a diſtant from the living God.</p>
               <p>Therefore with pitty unto thy Soul <hi>Willam Wilſon,</hi> who is now placed in <hi>VVindermer</hi> to Preach unto people there do I ſpeak, and alſo deſire thee to beware and take heed what thou doſt againſt the Lord and his people, whom he hath raiſed up by his Power and they muſt bear Teſtimony to his Holy Name, which is but little known, and much leſs regarded by a prophane people, whoſe Lives and Converſations is not converſant with the great God of Heaven and Earth, as they ought to be, neither hath their being with him as they ſhould therefore was a neceſſity upon us to declare his bleſſed Truth unto Gods witneſs in man, that they might come to heare and underſtand the things that belong to their everlaſting peace, to their mortal Souls, and this is all (and ever was all) the end we have or ever had, in meeting; So were the place of your worſhip, that we whom God hath revealed his Son in, may not ſmother him, neither ſtrangle him the womb, but muſt let his mouth be open, who hath right to ſpeak, who ſpeaks from Heaven, whoſe voice we have heard, and ſhape wee have ſeen, and cannot but declare his love to all men on the face of the whole Earth, that they may have, and ſee, and underſtand, and not be Ignorant of the things of God, but have the knowledge of him whom to know is life, and this is the Subſtance in ſhort of what hath lain upon us this many years, even unto the Souls of people, that we may be clear of their blood, and our God in his Judging whether they will hear or forbear, this is our meſſuage and Service, we ow to our God, and duty unto his people, as all people are his by Creation, and of right his Son ſhould Raign in them; So we leave the work unto the Lord, who can work and none can hinder who hath the hearts of people in his diſpoſing, and can turn them as he pleaſes and this is he whom we own, and in whoſe name we truſt, whatever we ſuffer for the ſame, we are freely given up as into the hands of a faithful Creator, who is God over all bleſſed of ever and for evermore; So now I ſay unto thee, <hi>VVillam Wilſon</hi> who is called of men Maſter and born up by an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward power without, and hath them to back and uphold thee, and is yet dark and ignorant of the power of God within, which is the higher power, even God to dwell in us, and walk in us according to his promiſe of old, which is made good to us in our age, and we muſt confeſs <hi>Chriſt</hi> before men, who is Gods righteouſneſs and Gods great power and Salvation unto loſt man, and as I ſaid before, he muſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47206:36"/>not be ſmothered in the Womb, but muſt have his liberty to ſpeak in his people.</p>
               <p>And if thou take this ill, out and call it a provocation or diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and ſo do evil and intreat his people evil, for their work and Service, the Lord will reward the there after. Therefore this is the pitty was in my heart at the moving to write this unto thee, that as thou art provoked to wrath and fury, as was plainly ſeen in thee, who would not let God Meſſengers declare their meſſuage, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver unto people what God had to ſay by them, who may be might never have had the like upon them there again, but cauſed them abuſively to be halled out of our peaceable Meeting; So I ſay take heed believes that thou do not provoke the Lord our God to Anger and ſore diſpleaſure againſt thee, even for ſo doing, for the Lord will take notice of thoſe things, and reward every man according to his works be they good or be they evil, therefore I ſay let things alone and do not provoke the Lord to Anger, by thy caſting them to ſuffer, but rather ſeek to turn away his wrath, while it is kindled but a little, and this is part of what aroſe in my mind unto thee, to aquaint thee with, and inform thee of, and adviſe thee to, whether thou wilt hear or forbear, it is in pitty to thy Soul, and for the preventing of further trouble thereof, which will not be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away if thou perſiſt herein, and do evil to thoſe people; So ſay not afterwards that thou was not warned, for in plain words from the mouth of thy friend, thou art warned, as well as the people, by one whoſe life is given up unto God in my meaſure, to ſerve the living God in my day, nor doubting nor fearing what man can do unto me, for my heavenly Teſtimony that God hath given me to bear in this bleſſed day of his love, which is offered unto all mankind upon the face of the whole Earth, ſo the wo and trouble will be unto them that ſeeks to ſtop the Current of his love from runing freely, as from Veſſel to Veſſel, that as we have freely received, we may freely give, ſo this is all at preſent as a gentle warning in love unto thee, to prevent the danger that may come by doing of evil to thy Neighbours, which thou ought to love, as thy ſelf, or elſe thou art guilty of the breach of Gods Commandment, and doth the things thou ought not to do therefore I ſay again, be warned who is a lover of thy Immortal Soul, whoſe name is known unto the world to be.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>VVillam Wilſon</hi> of <hi>Longdalechappellſteel.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:47206:36"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
